<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tears shed in the behalf of his dear mother the Church of England, and her sad distractions gathered and brought into this small paper vessell for the use of the vulgar, and common people, not to play with religion / by her adopted son, Daniel Getsius ...</title>
            <author>Getsius, Daniel, 1592-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 156 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 78 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42672</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G632</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31519</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12040967</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12040967</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52979</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42672)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52979)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1011:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Tears shed in the behalf of his dear mother the Church of England, and her sad distractions gathered and brought into this small paper vessell for the use of the vulgar, and common people, not to play with religion / by her adopted son, Daniel Getsius ...</title>
                  <author>Getsius, Daniel, 1592-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 144 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.L. ... for Tho. Robinson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52979:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52979:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TEARS SHED <hi>In the behalf of his dear Mother the</hi> CHURCH of ENGLAND, And her ſad Diſtractions: gathered, and brought into this ſmall Paper veſſell, for the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the vulgar, and Common people, not to play with Religion.</hi> By her adopted Son, DANIEL GETSIUS <hi>Miniſter of the word at Stoke-Gabriell in</hi> Devon.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Epheſ. 4.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>That we henceforth be no more Children, toſſed to and fro, and carried about with every wind of doctrine, by the ſleight of men, and cunning craftineſſe whereby they ly in wait to deceive.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD.</hi> Printed, by <hi>A. L.</hi> Printer to the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, for <hi>Tho. Robinſon,</hi> Anno 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:52979:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52979:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Venerable FRANCIS ROUS Eſq; one of the Honourable Councill of State, &amp; Provoſt of <hi>Eaton</hi> Colledge. <hi>Alſo to the</hi> Worſhipfull ARTHUR UPTON of LUPTON Eſq; <hi>And the</hi> Worſhipfull JOHN HALE of BOW<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RINGSLEIGH Eſq; Juſtices of the peace, in the County of <hi>Devon.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Ayly experience proves that of <hi>Seneca</hi> too true: <hi>None is ſo happy in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, but that ſometimes hee is deceived,</hi> For the greateſt part of men are thus affected, ſaith the Comick, humble they are, and promiſe much whilſt they are ſuitors for favours, but aſſoon as they have obtained them, of all men they are the worſt and moſt deceitfull: men even make haſt to forget good turn's, <hi>as God himſelf com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines by the Pſalmiſt of his Iſrael;</hi> a vice of vices, <hi>Ingratum ſi dixeris, Omnia dixeris: Non digni dandis, quia ingrati datis;</hi> unworthy of any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour,
<pb facs="tcp:52979:3"/>becauſe unthankfull for the leaſt. <hi>Invitat ad magna qui gratanter acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit modica, &amp; ſpem de futuris recipit, qui tranſacta beneficia recognoſcit.</hi> Many are the favours I have received of your hands, <hi>Honourable &amp; Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> of which I may truly ſay as <hi>Seneca</hi> of <hi>Furmius</hi> to <hi>Auguſtus;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. 22. de benif. c. 25.</note> 
               <hi>Hanc unam Caeſar habeo injuriam tuam, effeciſti ut viverem &amp; morerer ingratus.</hi> I well hoped before this time to have freed my ſelf in ſome ſort by a ſmall teſtimony of my thankfull heart, but the multitude of impediments and ſecond thoughts made mee to lay it aſide for a while. And now at length I humbly preſent this as a mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; innocent monument of my grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude. <hi>In magnis voluiſſe ſat eſt.</hi> It may proclaim and publiſh my obligation to you. And aſſure your ſelves that beſides theſe few lines to the common and vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar people, I ſhall alwayes contend and ſtrive by my dayly prayers to my good God for you, to bee privately thankfull: I humbly take my leave, and unfained<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remain.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>To you Honourable and Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in all humility devoted DANIEL GETSIUS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:52979:3"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian and Charitable <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MAny have excellently writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of the emendation of time, I wiſh we had ſuch effectuall motives and perſwaſions to amend ours; For in this <hi>Criſis</hi> of diſtempered humours, ſuch is the condition of moſt hearers, that men of God, lovers of God, and their neighbours, can hardly beſpeake the enemies of the Church, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently State (ſeeing that when the Churches quiet is diſturbed the Commonwealth will not long be ſettled) but he ſhall procure many enemies to himſelfe. Every one is jealous that ſomewhat is meant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his <hi>Diana</hi> or <hi>Helena.</hi> For my part, though I am no Native borne, yet with a great ſumme obtained I freedome, as he in the <hi>Acts.</hi> 22.28. Not to interpoſe my ſelfe betweene
<pb facs="tcp:52979:4"/>the affaires of the times, leaving them to them, to whom they belong, as a Stranger I am <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>non prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribo, ſed ſubſcribo:</hi> yet <hi>ad publicum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendium omnes concurrant.</hi> Therefore I thought it my duty as a ſon of the Church, to endeavour to leſſen (if I cannot quench) the fire. Some it may be ſee ſmoak, <hi>in favilla eſt,</hi> the fire is covered: But I muſt tell them it is wild-fire. The ſudden and violent o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration former times have diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in both <hi>Germany's High and Lowe.</hi> Concerning the materialls in this pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, I ſay as <hi>I. Lipſius</hi> of his <hi>Politick Cento, nihil meum &amp; omne meum,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the end, &amp; that is all: Farewell, and pray with me for vnity, which is the preſerver of Church and State, if it be in the truth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:52979:4"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> GOd wrought all, for himſelf, man, and to have a Church.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> The Nature, and Members of the Church.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> What it is that maketh the Church, with her markes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> The prerogatives of the Church.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> The good things which are afforded to a Nation and place, where God ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers a Church.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> Sins expoſing a Church and Nation to Gods wrath.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> Signes generall, and particular of Gods anger with a Nation, and the Church in the ſame.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8.</hi> The means to recall God from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting, and to keep him with us.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi> Of falſe Prophets, or Teachers.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10.</hi> A brief hiſtoricall relation of the
<pb facs="tcp:52979:5"/>reterated troubles in both <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny's,</hi> by Anabaptiſts, and other Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11.</hi> A ſhort ejaculation to God for the Church.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52979:5"/>
            <head>Tears ſhed in behalfe of his Dear <hi>Mother</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lmighty and all-ſufficient God, willing to manifeſt his glory abroad, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out himſelfe, was pleaſed to doe it by divers meanes; the firſt is the Creation of all things out of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but man eſpecially to his Image, that is, holy, wiſe, and righteous, yet mutable by his voluntary fall to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt his Makers glory.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:52979:6"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Glory of God is twofold.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> inward and eſſentiall, which is his Majeſty, known only to himſelf;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.18 <hi>Iſa:</hi> 42.8.</note> this <hi>Moſes</hi> out of infirmity deſired to ſee: And God will give to no other. This glory Chriſt had with the Father before the world was, that is,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17.5.</note> divine Majeſty from all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; which towards the world was for a time clouded by the vail of his fleſh,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.7.</note> in the forme of a ſervant.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Gods outward or exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal glory, is the index or diſcoverer, of the former, ſhining outwardly in his works, which have certain marks and footſteps of the Divine glory imprinted in them. Gods inward glory dependeth abſolutely from his nature,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 7.2.</note> by which God cannot but be the God of glory <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. But his outward glory depends from his moſt free will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, working all things after the Counſell of his own Will.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.11.</note>
               </p>
               <p>By outward meanes, illuſtrating
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52979:6"/>his inward glory, diverſly and ſundry wayes; the Creation one way, the fall of man another way: In reſpect of this, as the wiſdome of God is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> manyfold,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.10</note> or having curious variety in it; ſo may this out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward manifeſtation of Gods glory, not unfitly, be ſaid to be manifold and full of variety.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt way then or mean is cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, firſt in execution, and therefore without doubt, firſt alſo in the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors intention, whereby this infinite wiſdome, goodnes, and power is ſet forth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The next place we aſſigne to the Creation of man, to evidence his goodnes in a more ſpeciall way, as having in a manner made all for him, making him to have dominion over the works of his hands,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8 6.</note> putting all things under his feet.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third place we give to the permiſſion of the fall and ſinne, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing given him not <hi>impotentiam caden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di,</hi> an impotencie to fall, but <hi>poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52979:7"/>non cadendi,</hi> a power not to fall if he pleaſed; which, he abuſing brought himſelfe, and all mankind into death and miſery, by tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the command given him, and ſo becommeth a mean to ſet forth Gods juſtice and mercy; his juſtice in pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhing this rebellion with eternal fire; and his mercy, in giving his only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten ſonne, <hi>that whoſoever, of the now loſt off ſpring of Adam ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in him, ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life,</hi> as a gift of his infinite mercy:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3, 16, 17, 18.</note> 
                  <hi>but he that believed not, ſhould be condemned, becauſe he beleeved not in the name of the only begotten Sonne of God.</hi> And this is a third way, whereby God ſets forth the outward glory of his Juſtice and infinite mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A fourth way is conſiſting in the free gift of his word, and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, to acquaint loſt man with his forlorne eſtate, and to diſcover a way how to get out of the ſame; The law is given to diſcover the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52979:7"/>firſt; and the Goſpel ſhew's a way how to get out.</p>
               <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> the Law</note> The word of the Law taketh place firſt, which being preached, doth firſt bring man to a ſight of ſin,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20. <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20. diſcovering to man his manifold defects and ſwervings from the law.</p>
               <p n="2">2. After this it propoſeth Gods curſe due to ſinne <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.26. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10. 3ly. Whence ariſeth anxiety,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.26. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10.</note> fear, and that grief the Apoſtle cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth according to the world 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.10. 4ly. By all which acts man is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to entertain the grace of the Goſpel, which is appointed for ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.10</note> 
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.13. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. <hi>for them who labour and are heavy laden Mat.</hi> 11.28.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.13.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.18</note> 
                  <hi>For thoſe who are poore and of a contrite ſpirit Iſa.</hi> 66.2. Then the Goſpel taketh the ſecond place,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2</hi> the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel.</note> which</p>
               <p>Offereth to the ſinners contrite with the ſenſe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and feeling of their ſinnes, and Gods wrath for the ſame, the grace of God in Chriſt,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52979:8"/>revealing the myſtery which was kept ſecret ſince the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.25. <hi>chap.</hi> 10.16</note> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.25. ſhewing how by faith they may become partakers of the ſame. <hi>cap.</hi> 10.16.</p>
               <p>Then ſecondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the Goſpel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth faith, as an effectuall, and powerfull inſtrument. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16. by the word preached and heard,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16. <hi>chap.</hi> 10.17</note> 
                  <hi>cap.</hi> 10.17. and thus,</p>
               <p>Thirdly it applyeth grace to the beleever, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> according to Chriſts pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.24. <hi>Verily, verily, I ſay unto you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.24.</note> 
                  <hi>he that heareth my word, and beleeveth on him that ſent me, hath everlaſting life, and ſhall not come into condemnation, but is paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from death unto life.</hi> From this ariſeth in our hearts.</p>
               <p>Ioy, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> becauſe <hi>being juſtified by faith we have peace with God, through Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1</p>
               <p>Griefe; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> for diſcovering by the Goſpel ſo great a mercy of God the Father towards us, man cannot but grieve, and be aſhamed of thoſe ſins
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52979:8"/>wherewith he hath offended him. This is a far other griefe from that of the world, which therefore the Apoſtle calleth the griefe according to God 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.10.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.10.</note> Bringing with it a new man, in mind, will, affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and all his actions, from evill to good, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.15.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 34.15.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And here again the Law becomes ſubſervient to the Goſpel. For ſeeing this change is not to be wrought af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mans pleaſure, but according to the will of God expreſſed in his Law.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.20. <hi>Ezc.</hi> 20.18.19. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.8.9. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.8.18 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.105. <hi>Ier.</hi> 31.33. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.20. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.18, 19. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.8, 9. 2 <hi>Col.</hi> 8.18. Therefore the Law here offers it ſelf again to be a Rule to us in this new life <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.105. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.33. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. Thus it plainly appeareth that God Almighty doth all for man. For man
<list>
                     <item>1. All things were created, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8. Even Angels to be his Miniſters, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.14.</item>
                     <item>2.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.14.</note> Gods Son deveſted himſelf for man, &amp; came down from Heaven, ſubmitted to that ſhamefull death
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52979:9"/>of the Croſſe to redeem him,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6, 7, 8.</note> 
                        <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6, 7, 8.</item>
                     <item>3. For mans ſake, God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to writing his will in his Law and Goſpel. That ſo man might</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>See his deformity by ſin, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.7.</note> and puniſhment deſerved; to ſeek for mercy. That man might ſecondly</p>
               <p>Get faith, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> to lay hold on Chriſt, to be ſaved by him from the evill of ſin, and puniſhment. And laſtly, to</p>
               <p>Gather men into a ſociety, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> or Company, <hi>who ſhould be his peculiar people,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 2, 13.</note> 
                  <hi>zealous of good works.</hi> Which people called out of the World and believing in Chriſt, make up his body ſpirituall, the Church, of which he is the head: And thus wee ſee all was done for the Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:52979:9"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> The Nature and Members of this myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call body of the Church.</head>
               <p>THe Church according to theſe premiſes, is an aſſembly or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of men, whom God by his Word and Spirit calleth out of the State of ſin, to the State of grace and glory. God calls men ordinarily by men, his Miniſters, who are his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors, beſeeching and praying men in Chriſts ſteed to be reconciled to God.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20.</note> The Church then is a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Called, and calling doth make up this Aſſembly we call the Church. From this Act of calling the Church hath her name in Hebrew <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation or Company, called to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; in the Greek <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> from calling out, namely of ſome from others:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.19. <hi>Chap.</hi> 17.6. <hi>vers</hi> 14.</note> I have choſen you out of the World; becauſe they were given him out of the World: And being thus called out, they are no more of the World. They are now to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52979:10"/>be a particular peculiar Aſſembly or Company diſtinguiſhed from the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.1.</note> Thus was Abraham <hi>called out of</hi> Ur <hi>of Chaldea,</hi> Paul <hi>out of the Aſſembly of Phariſees,</hi> others, yea all out of the Company, and ſtate of ſinners, the power of darkneſſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Act.</hi> 26.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13. The power of Satan, <hi>Act.</hi> 26.18. To be of the number of Gods people, who are in the ſtate of grace, to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9.</note> To Gods King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.12.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.12.</note> We may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve here by the way, the high di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnity of every one effectually called; he is by calling intitled to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and glory of God: an high or ſupernaturall calling,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.14. An heavenly calling,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.1. Compare <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.22,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.22, 23.</note> 23. The Church then properly is the Aſſembly of the Lord, or the Lords Aſſembly. This Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly hath Chriſt loved, <hi>and given him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for her,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.25.</note> Eph. 5.25. <hi>He hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed the ſame with his own bloud,</hi> Act. 20.28.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28.</note> 
                  <hi>Her he purifieth, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweth eternall life upon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.23.</note> Eph. 5.23.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52979:10"/>The matter therefore of the Church is an Aſſembly of men, elected and called, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.1, 2. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.1, 2, 3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. If the Church be
<list>
                     <item>1. An Aſſembly, one alone cannot be a Church, as <hi>Elias</hi> conceived, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 19.10. For one is not a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, flock, a multitude of believers,<note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 19.10.</note> a holy nation. City of God, the Congregation of the juſt, as the Church is ſaid to be 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.2, 3. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Act.</hi> 4.32.</item>
                     <item>2. The Church again is an Aſſembly, of men, not of Angels, who nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are men, nor choſen, or called as men.</item>
                     <item>3. Thirdly, the Church is a Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, or Aſſembly of the elect or choſen, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28, 29, 30.</item>
                     <item>4. Fourthly, It is an Aſſembly of men elected and called, &amp; therefore it is not ſufficient to be elected, calling is required alſo. Election appoints them, but calling makes them
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52979:11"/>actuall members, &amp; declares them. Thus <hi>Paul</hi> by deſtination was a member of the Church in his Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſaiſme, even then when he perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted the Church: But by calling he became an actuall member, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.15. To the contrary, whereas ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated perſons, and ſuch as are newly come into the Churches pale to be inſtructed, but are not as yet baptized, may be elected &amp; cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; as may appear by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of thoſe, who were excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated by the Jewiſh Church, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 9.22. Of the Thief on the Croſſe, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.43. And <hi>Cornelius, Act.</hi> 10.2, 34. Theſe therefore may be alſo members of the Church, and are indeed, as many as have true faith. Children alſo, and mad men belong to the Church.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Outward by Condition of their birth, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> which cauſeth them to be called holy or Saints, being born of faithfull parents, either one or both, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:52979:11"/>
               <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> they belong to the Church inward or inviſible, by the gift of inward calling, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.29. By which known to the Lord are thoſe who are his, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19.</note> Thoſe who are deaf may not onely be partakers, of the inward, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo outward calling; not by hearing indeed, but by ſight: as often as Chriſt Cruciſied is ſet forth to the faithfull in the Goſpel and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> What it is that makes the Church, with her true markes.</head>
               <p>THat which gives being to this holy Aſſembly, the Church, is, that the ſame is called by the word and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, out of the State of ſin, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſtate of grace. All and every member of the Church are ſuch by calling. Thus <hi>Abraham</hi> is called out of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r</hi> of the Caldeans, <hi>Paul</hi> out of Phariſaiſme, all that are Members
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52979:12"/>of the Church, by being called out of the ſtate of ſin, into the ſtate of grace. <hi>Outwardly</hi> by the word, whereby alſo are called eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe that are not elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.16. <hi>and</hi> 22.14. <hi>Inwardly</hi> by the holy Spirit according to Gods purpoſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. and of election <hi>Chap.</hi> 9.11. belonging onely to the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.29. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. Hence is the Church called and ſaid to be,
<list>
                     <item>1. Viſible, according to outward cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling by the word, being ſenſible or ſubject to ſenſe. And</item>
                     <item>2. Inviſible, in reſpect of the inward calling by the Spirit, not being ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, or ſubject to ſenſe, onely known to him who calleth, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. The Lord knoweth who are his; and is alſo diſcerned by thoſe who are called <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.17. For none knoweth that new name in the white ſtone, ſaving him that hath received it. Chriſt therefore ſaith; the Kingdome of God commeth not with outward obſervation, or ſhew, but is within. <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.20, 21.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52979:12"/>that is in ſecret <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 45.13. The Kings Daughter is all glorious with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and ſo we confeſſe in our Creed to beleeve the Church; and faith is of things not ſeen <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1. Yet the Church is viſibly known by a marke purely divine, the word, which mark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out the Church two ways infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and ſenſibly.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Infallibly, becauſe the Church is a body, or company of thoſe, who embrace the word of God; and every company or body embracing the word of God, is the Church; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Chriſts word <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.47. <hi>He that is of God heareth Gods word,</hi> and <hi>verſ.</hi> 31. <hi>If you continue in my word, then are you my Diſciples indeed. Chap.</hi> 10.27. <hi>My ſheep hear my voyce,</hi> and v. 5. <hi>they know not the voyce of ſtrangers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, the viſible Church is known ſenſibly by the word, which may be ſeen, read, and heard. The preaching of the word, and profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſame, as alſo the uſe of the Sacraments are ſecondary markes,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52979:13"/>together with order &amp; diſcipline flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the former, which is pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly divine; But theſe are of a mixt nature, partly divine and partly hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, in reſpect of mans help in the adminiſtration of the ſame: whence they are more or leſſe pure and incorrupt, according to the diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of the Prerogatives of the Church.</head>
               <p>HAving ſhewed the nature of the Church, in the next place, let us view the priviledges, and dignities of the ſame; for God hath graced this Aſſembly we call the Church with ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial prerogatives above all aſſembly's in this vniverſe: all muſt be ſubſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient to her, <hi>Kings muſt be nurſing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and Queens nurſing mothers. Iſa</hi> 43.23. Theſe dignities may be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered either in</p>
               <p n="1">1. Generall. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.1. we read of the enlargment, and advancement thereof under the name of a tent,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52979:13"/>wherein anciently they dwelt; the ſtretching out the Curtains, the lengthning of the cords, the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth on the right hand and on the left, inheriting the Gentiles, and making the deſolate Cities to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited; what meaneth it but the enlargement of the Church Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an; conſiſting joyntly of Jew and Gentile. There was a time when it did belong to the Jews, and to thoſe that did joyn with them, <hi>but now Chriſt hath broken down the partition wall,</hi> and hath laid all the world com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 2 13.</note> now he hath enlarged the Church, and ſpread it all the world over. This is that <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeakes of <hi>Act.</hi> 10.34. <hi>Of a truth I perceive, that God is no accepter of perſons, but in every nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he that feareth Him, and worketh righteouſnes, is accepted of him,</hi> ſee Mat. 8.11. The particular dignities and priviledges of the Church are theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt the Church is Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, namely myſticall, whoſe head and very ſoule is Chriſt, quickning
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52979:14"/>the ſame with his ſpirit, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.22, 23. Hence whatſoever is done to any of the Church, he taketh it to himſelf, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.4. <hi>Saul, Saul, why perſecuteſt thou me? Membris adhuc poſitis in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, caput clamat in coelis, &amp; non di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cebat, quid perſequeris fideles meos?</hi> Auguſt. <hi>Serm.</hi> 11. <hi>de anct.</hi> Whileſt his members were as yet on earth, the head cries out in heaven, and he ſaith not, why perſecuteſt thou my faithful ones, but why perſecuteſt thou me?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the Church is Chriſts Love,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 45.20. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.31.</note> Spouſe, Siſter and Queen, Daughter of a King, yea his Wife. This is a neere relation and partaking: <hi>A man ſhall be joyned to his Wife, ſaith the Apoſtle, and they two ſhall be one fleſh.</hi> This is an ineffable myſtery, the Beleevers heart may feel it, no tongue can expreſſe it, here all lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage is loſt, and admiration ſeals up every lip: Principality and powers, nature and reaſon, men &amp; Angels ſtand amazed at it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, this holy Spouſe begetteth
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52979:14"/>Children to Chriſt,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23</note> by the ſeed of the word, and miniſtry of the ſame; therefore is ſhe called <hi>the Mother of us all, Gal.</hi> 4.26. And after they are borne. ſhe feedeth her Babes by the ſame word,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2.</note> as with milke and ſtrong meate. The ſincere word of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this nature, that without any mixture of humane addition, it ſerves for a moſt fit nouriſhment of our ſoules; whence is that ſaying of old, <hi>Qui non habet Eccleſiam matrem, non habet Deum patrem:</hi> He or ſhee who acknowledgeth not the Church for his Mother, hath not God for his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Theſe her Children are a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Prieſts, a holy nation, <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.6. The Lords inheritance, and his flock, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 10. All which and many more expreſſions the Seripture affords; whereby it plainly appears how dear and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious the Church is to God: I am my beloveds &amp; my beloved is mine, <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.3. All true believers, mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of this Church are his, by a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52979:15"/>propriety: Wee are thine, thou never bareſt rule over them, they were not called by thy name, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.19. The Divells are his vaſſals, the wicked of the world his priſoners; The faithfull onely are his Jewels, friends, brethren, members, his Spouſe; His by all the relations of intimateneſſe, that can be named.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> The good things which flow from this neer relation to the Church and place where the ſame is gathered.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SAmpſon</hi> (who was a Type of Chriſt) comes not empty handed to his Wife; Chriſt Jeſus who hath choſen the Church for his Wife, lov's his Wife with a true love, and therefore ſhe is ſure of abundance of bleſſings. All grace to our ſouls, all good to our bodies, all peace that may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern this life, or that to come is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived to us through Chriſt the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band of the Church. Whatſoever good deſcends from God to us, is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:52979:15"/>granted through Chriſt, wee are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected in Chriſt as the head, <hi>redeemed by Chriſt from all iniquity, and puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to himſelf to be a peculiar people</hi> (that is the Church) <hi>zealous of good workes, Tit.</hi> 2.14. Wee are ingrafted into Chriſt as Members of his Body, and at length we ſhall be ſaved by him. God gives to all gifts, but they are onely true comforts, to thoſe which enjoy them, as members of Chriſts body the Church. Amongſt his Love tokens, which Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowes on his Spouſe the Church for grace and ornament, the Jewel of the word and miniſtery is the chiefeſt, ſo the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> 147.19, 20. Hee ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his word unto <hi>Jacob,</hi> his Statutes and his judgements unto <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he hath not dealt ſo with any nation. The benefits of this are expreſſed in the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> by ſix Couples; where your are to note, and obſerve.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That David ſpeaks eſpecially of the word of the Goſpel,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſe</hi> 7, 8.</note> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts, and rejoyceth the heart. Marke likewiſe</item>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:52979:16"/>
                  <item>2. The names he gives to the word. Then</item>
                  <item>3. The benefits of it by couples; and that by way of oppoſition to all other inſtruction out of the pale of the Church, that is in oppoſition to all meer humane learning: plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewing the happineſſe of them, who are made partakers of the word.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt name is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Thora á</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>jecit, projecit.</hi> To caſt forth from him: hence <hi>Thora</hi> a doctrine uttered, caſt forth by a Teacher to inſtruct others, here eſpecially concerning the will of God, wherefore the word <hi>Jehovah</hi> is added.<note place="margin">Verſe 7.</note> It's two excellencies, and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects are, integrity and reſtitution, or reſtoring the ſoul, Converſion.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Integrity, the word of God is perfect, that is, diſcovers more plainly and fully to his Church or people the will of God, then any doctrine or learning that is taught out of the Church by any, though never ſo learned. Philoſophers had
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52979:16"/>onely the knowledge of God, by the Creatures, Sun, Moon, Stars, and others on Earth, in the Air, and the Sea, whereby God did evidence his goodneſſe, wiſdome, and power: his will &amp; nature is not evidenced fully or perfectly.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Excellencie, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> or the ſecond effect of Gods Law is, to convert the Soul; that is, Gods heavenly doctrine diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers the remedy againſt all evills which proceed from ſin, &amp; withall the way to get out. But humane wiſdome at the fartheſt brings only to the ſight of our miſeries; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing no remedy, but leav's men with great penſiveneſſe, and care of minde, to enquire the cauſe of that horrible ruine in man, the little world, and chief of all viſible crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: which made <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> to utter this complaint, that nature was rather a Stepdame, then a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Mother to mankinde. Thus men out of the Church are left without any remedy, ſpending and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52979:17"/>waſting themſelves with moſt ſad and ſorrowfull complaints; Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Gods word ſheweth to thoſe of the church a plain way to get out of their wretched eſtate.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond name given to the word is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> from <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Gnud,</hi> to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify; the Law or word is called a Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony becauſe it beareth witneſſe of Gods will, which he manifeſteth to us in his word, chiefly the Goſpel. Truth, and making wiſe the ſimple, are the two excellencies of this Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony. The Word of God witneſſeth firſt
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>What is that good, acceptable, and perfect will of God.</hi> Rom. 12.2.</item>
                     <item>2. Secondly, being applyed to our thoughts, words or works as a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in our conſciences, it either accuſeth, if they anſwere not the pattern, God hath given in his Word: or elſe excuſeth, if they be conformable to the word.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third generall excellency of the word, and firſt of this Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:52979:17"/>
               <p n="1">1. Truth <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, faithfull, certain, firm, incorrupt, which is allwayes the ſame, a ſingular excellency of the word expreſſing fully the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Author of this word, <hi>who is Amen, yeſterday and to day,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.8.</note> 
                  <hi>and the ſame for ever.</hi> By this Chriſt prayeth the Father to ſanctify his Diſciples, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17.17. <hi>Sanctify them by thy word, thy word is truth,</hi> as if he ſaid; onely that doctrine which is delivered in thy word, is the truth; All other doctrines are er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous, whence it is that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences cannot be ſetled by them, but are left uncertain, allwayes doubting, never fixed and ſetled, and ſo at length are precipitated into the gulf of everlaſting deſpair.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The other excellency or effect of the word, and fourth in number is making wiſe the ſimple; No hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane wiſdome ſurpaſſeth this of the word, and whoſoever will be truely wiſe, muſt repair to the word of God. This doth
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:52979:18"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Reveal Gods will towards us, which no other doctrine can. <hi>This</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. Sheweth us our wounds &amp; diſeaſes, and withall preſcribes the remedy.</item>
                     <item>3. This diſcovers the plots and ſtratagems of Satan againſt Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, and teacheth us how to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void, or to meet them. To be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in the word is the way to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine true wiſdome, which the worldly wiſe never meet with; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he deny his earthly wiſdome, and become ſimple, as a babe, a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fool, humble, lowly, harmeleſſe, not examining things by the weak rule of his crooked reaſon, but ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer himſelf to be guided by Gods Word, although the ſame ſeem ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo fooliſh. Then will he finde indeed, that the word, which the men of this World deſpiſe as foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, hath more wiſdome in it then all the World. They ſhall acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that, which in their eſteem formerly was but weak, and of no power or efficacy to ſalvation, to be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:52979:18"/>more ſtrong and powerfull then all conceited eloquence.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The third name, or title of the word is, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> viſitations, ſtatutes, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> precepts, commiſſions, charges, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto men carefully to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved; the tranſgreſſions whereof God hath threatned to viſit and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh. This is the reaſon of the name. The effects or excellencies of theſe ſtatutes, are theſe two; They are right, And rejoyce the heart, being the fifth, and ſixth excellencies of the word.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> from a word ſignifying right or ſtraight, even and plain; and therefore pleaſing the eye, and ſo the heart: things crooked, rough, and uneven doe diſpleaſe. Gods word is right, communicating to us the ſtraighteſt rule of life. It leads us not <hi>per Ambages</hi> in ways farre about, but in the directeſt line to heaven: whoſoever keepeth the ſame cannot chooſe but enjoy a quiet, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a rejoycing heart, and joyfull
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:52979:19"/>conſcience. The doctrine taught in the Chuch is plain and perſpicuous, having noe knotty, and obſcure quirks in it, leading out of the way, into precipices: But to the contrary humane doctrines are various, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, of inextricable labyrinths; out of which the wit of man is not able to get. Heavenly doctrine, eſpecially that of the Goſpel, freeth the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience formerly entangled, remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth all doubts, ſcruples, perplexiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and anxieties of mind, contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by humane learning. It doth bring them into the right way to the ſafe haven of reſt; which cannot but rejoyce the heart: And this is the ſixth excellencie, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> or effect of the word of God, belonging eſpecially to the Goſpel. For this only makes the heart joyfull, and appeaſeth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience before God, which no hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane learning can doe; neither the law, by reaſon of our corruption, which it rather ſtirreth then appeaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. And although it be the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:52979:19"/>of the Croſs, yet it is joyned w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ſuch comforts, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> keep up the heart, and make it overcome at laſt all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fficulties. The fourth name or title of the word is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> precepts, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding or forbidding with autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and power to binde, or giving advice by way of perſwaſion, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; the two excellent effects are purity, and light. It commandeth that which is good ſo plainly, and forbids that which is bad, that it may not be hidden, except it be from thoſe who are loſt, in whom the God of this world hath blinded their eies, leſt the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt ſhould enlighten their minds 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3, 4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> The ſeaventh excellency of the word is to be pure having no dregs of corrupt opinions mixed with it, nor admitting any wickednes. Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane learning is many ways defiled, even in theſe things wherein they ſeeme moſt wiſe: men in their lawes ſhould diſcover moſt wiſdome, yet in them alſo they appear but meer men, as is plain in the lawes of the <hi>Spartans</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:52979:20"/>admitting adultery; the <hi>Lacedemoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> permitted theft, and other filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. But the Law of God is pure, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing no wickednes, and the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel is not only pure, but ſheweth alſo and diſcovereth the fountain where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we may waſh and cleanſe our ſelves. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> The Eighth Excellency of the word is to enlighten the eies: The heavenly doctrine revealed in the word, drives away all darkneſſe of the mind, ignorance of God, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullnes, carnall ſecurity, diffidence, and other motions, ſwerving from the Law of God. It openeth the eies of our mind to ſee our filthines, to perceive the greatneſſe of our ſins and miſeries, and holdeth out a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent remedy: when in the mean while they without the Church, are oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the greateſt blindnes, neither knowing nor underſtanding their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, much leſs ſeeking to get out.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The fifth name or title of the word is, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> feare, reverence; pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to God-ward expreſſeth her ſelfe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:52979:20"/>a reverentiall feare: the Excellencies are purity and perpetuity; enduring for ever. The fear or reverence, that is, thereligion and worſhip preſcribed in Gods word, is cleane from all filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, becauſe God requires to be worſhiped in ſpirit and truth, and with pure hands. But mans wiſdome, which is attained by meditation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the creatures, may come to the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of a God, but who that God is, vvhat he is, and how he is to be ſerved or worſhiped, here they are divided. Some of thoſe deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of the word faine a plurality of Gods, ſerving him rather like beaſts, or divells, then men, by their humane ſacrifices, and all manner of abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable luſts. But, Gods word is pure, allowing no multitude of Gods, but one only, and preſcribing a pure and clean worſhip, ſpirituall, and beſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his nature. The tenth excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of the word is duration; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> The heavenly doctrine is ſtill one and the ſame in ſubſtance, by reaſon of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:52979:21"/>its ſpirituall purity, which admitteth of no variation much leſſe corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and therefore muſt of neceſſity abide forever. All humane inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, have not only varied, but came at laſt to nothing.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> The ſixth and laſt title of the word is, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Judgments, becauſe,
<list>
                     <item>1. The word doth contain Gods judiciall ſentence concerning our thoughts, words, and workes. Then</item>
                     <item>2. Secondly, according to the word, we ſhall all be judged.</item>
                     <item>3. Thirdly, And according to the word, we are to judg of our thoughts words and deeds.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The two excellencyes are truth, and righteouſnes; the word doth declare Gods truth and righteouſnes, in his providentiall adminiſtration of all things.</p>
               <p>The Eleaventh excellency of the word, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> is truth, that is that doctrine which is the rule of mans life, given him by God, hath neither falſhood nor vanity in it, and therefore ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:52979:21"/>to the ſame we order our life, and converſation; other inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions given by man are full of error, falſhood and deceit, ſo that thoſe that follow that crooked rule, muſt needs be much out of the way. The Twelfth and laſt excellency of the word is righteouſnes: there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the word you may find fault with, but is abſolutely perfect; whereas humane lawes, ordinances and ſtatutes, are unjuſt, and filthy, allowing that which is wicked, and forbidding oftentimes that which is good. But the word of God with it's teſtimonies, doctrines, precepts, and commandements, teaching the fear of God, is altogether juſt and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, happy therefore is that nation, where God hath been pleaſed to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Church for himſelf, &amp; is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to continue the ſame; this is it <hi>Moſes</hi> preſſeth to the Iſraelites, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.5, 6, 7, 8. <hi>I have taught you ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes and judgements, even as the Lord my God commanded me, that you
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:52979:22"/>ſhould do them in the Land where you go to poſſeſſe it. Keep therefore and do them, for this is your wiſdome, and your underſtanding in the ſight of the nations, which ſhall hear all theſe ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes and ſay, ſurely this great nation is a wiſe and underſtanding people, for what nation is there ſo great, that hath God ſo nigh unto them, as the Lord our God is in all things, that we call upon him for? And what nation is there ſo great, that hath ſtatutes &amp; judgements, ſo righteous, as all this law which I ſet before you this day?</hi> By theſe and the like <hi>Moſes</hi> evidenceth, that hee is not able to expreſſe the greatneſſe of the bleſſing of the word, which God doth grant to ſome nations, it is a privy bleſſing, which the Pſalmiſt in a ſingular manner ſets forth <hi>Pſalm</hi> 147.19, 20. Having mentioned many temporall bleſſings God had affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the Jews, whereof ſome were.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Common to them with other nations, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 16.17, 18. Snow, hore-froſt, and Ice, all for the fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:52979:22"/>of the earth, in common to all good and bad, within the pale of the Church, and without.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Peculiar to the Jews onely; and the ſame.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Temporall, the building of their City, ruined before by the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeans and the bringing them back out of the Babylonian Captivity. Others were.</item>
                  <item>2. Spirituall, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 19, 20. The gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to them his word, wherein he reveals his will to his Church, a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour not afforded to any nation beſides.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The Jewes had three Crowns which made them renowned and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous. The Crown of the Law, King, and Prieſt; of all three the Crown of the Law was moſt glorious, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by her Princes reign, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.15, 16. David <hi>therefore meditat's there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in night and day,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.2.</note> 
                  <hi>and makes the ſame his Councellour, in the morning when he roſe, and at night when he went to bed,</hi> Pſal. 119.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:52979:23"/>
               <p>I will adde one excellencie more aſſorded to this Nation, before all others in the World.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. This Nation was one of the firſt received the Goſpel.</item>
                  <item>2. This Nation did yeeld to the firſt Chriſtian Emperour <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, born at <hi>York,</hi> who gave peace and honour to the Church.</item>
                  <item>3. The third and greateſt Light, that did ſhine forth in darkeſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery to all the World was <hi>Wickliffe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. The firſt royall <hi>Martyr</hi> was <hi>Oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wald,</hi> who united the two Crowns of <hi>England and Scotland,</hi> after hee had much enlarged the bounds of Chriſts Kingdome with his own; in the end exchanged his Princely Diadem for a Crown of Matyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and ſo ſigned the Chriſtian faith with his royal bloud.</item>
                  <item>5. It was the firſt Kingdome, that ſhook Antichriſt fully out of the Saddle.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Now beſides theſe bleſſings afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Church; Empires, Kingdomes
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:52979:23"/>States and Commonwealths proſper and flouriſh with the Church; God hath a ſpeciall care of ſuch Lands, where his Church, and true religion find entertainment; The Kingdome of <hi>Iſrael</hi> flouriſhed even to the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of others, as long as true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion flouriſhed in the Church. But aſſoon as they fell off from God, and gloried onely in the Temple, the place was turned into an heap of ſtones, &amp; the people were diſperſed, without a King or Prophet, or any ſhew of a people of God. <hi>Aſia</hi> was once famous through the World, by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Churches in the ſame; the fame of their faith ſounded far and neer. Their place now is become a Receptacle for Mahomet, a Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue for Satan, and a Temple for Turkiſh Idolatry. That Nation then, Empire, Kingdome, &amp; State flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, where the Church flouriſhes in maintayning the truth of the word.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:52979:24"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Sins expoſing a Church and Nation to the wrath of God.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>1. FIrſt, Barrenneſſe</item>
                  <item>2. Cruell Uſage of his Saints and Meſſengers.</item>
                  <item>3. Light eſteem of the word of God.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Theſe ſtrip a Nation of thoſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings wherewith God hath graced them, and expoſe it to ſcorn and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Barrenneſſe, whether carnall or ſpiritual, hath alwayes been accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a Curſe; Johns Mother inſinuateth the one <hi>Luke</hi> 1.25. <hi>The Lord hath looked on mee to take away my reproach amongst men;</hi> and vvhen God gives ſalvation, he is ſaid to take avvay barreneſſe; Sing O barren; thou that didſt not bear, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.1. But vvhat are our fruits? the Catalogue of them vve have <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19, 20, 21. vvorks of the fleſh, ſpecially theſe, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riance, hatred, emulation, vvrath, ſtrife, ſedition, hereſy, envyings,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:52979:24"/>murther, drunkeneſſe, and revel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings: better to be barren, then bring forth ſuch fruits. Theſe vvere the fruits, of Sion and Jeruſalem, the Jevviſh Nation, and Church in our ſaviours dayes; therefore in his love to the people of Iſrael, zeal of their ſalvation, &amp; knowledge of their finall deſtruction at hand, in grief and pity he burſt out into tears: <hi>Oh that thou hadſt known in this thy day;</hi> a paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ſpeech abrupt or broken off, he could not ſpeak out the reſt for vveeping, by reaſon of thoſe things that were to come upon them. Abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of affectionate thoughts as it vvere thronging the heart, like ſome violent preſſe of people at a door, hinder each others paſſage, he blames and vvithall pittyeth them. <hi>O if thou hadſt known, at leaſt in this thy day,</hi> that is thy viſitation, this time wherein God calleth thee to repentance, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth peace to thee; underſtand hovv happy hadſt thou been, thou had'ſt eſcaped the determined de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:52979:25"/>Our ſaviour ſhevveth the end of ſuch barreneſſe plainly, <hi>John.</hi> 15.1. In the parable of the Vine. which ſpeaketh of every one in the Church, into vvhich they are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted by Baptiſme. Wee'l note theſe follovving degrees.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. They are barren, bear no fruit, this is the firſt ſtep into Hell; After vvhich</item>
                  <item>2. They are cut off from the Vine, cut it dovvn, ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.7. Why cumbreth it the ground? as if he ſhould ſay, they do vvith their bad example but marre others, and make them unfruitfull.</item>
                  <item>3. Being cut off from the Vine, they are caſt out of the Vineyard, that is the Church, they are not ſuffered to ſuck in Vaine the breaſts of her Conſolation, nor partake of her prayers; The Lord is moved to reject them, his labour not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing anſwered, he vvill pull down the fence, break dovvn the vvall, leave his ovvn Vineyard to vvaſt,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:52979:25"/>ovvn it who will <hi>Iſa</hi> 5.6. What more fearfull then for a man to be left by God, to become a Lodge for Divels, luſts, and vvaſting ſins, till at laſt by death he is cut off. The Lord brings on them this judgement in manner follovving.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item>1. By death, cut him down, bring the axe, the pruning knife hath done no good, hew him down by death, from the Miniſtry under which he hath been ſo long fruitleſſe.</item>
                  <item>2. Taking away the meanes of fruitfullneſſe, the Clouds ſhall not rain upon it. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.6. The means of ſalvation his word and Miniſtry ſhall be taken away.</item>
                  <item>3. Blowing on the gifts they have already, they ſhall doe them no good; the unprofitable ſervant had his Talent taken away.</item>
               </list>
               <p>This curſe is ſo eminent upon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men, of good parts once, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring themſelves with themſelves now, a man may ſay with the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Figge-tree <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.20.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:52979:26"/>
                  <hi>how ſoon is the figge tree withered.</hi> And this a further degree.</p>
               <p n="4">4ly. They vvither receiving no life of ſap from him that gives the ſap of life to all. And being</p>
               <p n="5">5ly. Withered, they are bound up into faggots, like the tares in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to bundles <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.30.</p>
               <p n="6">6ly. Thus fagotted up they are caſt into the fire.</p>
               <p n="7">7ly. Where they burn and frye in theſe quenchleſſe flames, ever frying, never dying.</p>
               <p>The ſecond provoking ſin is cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, a ſinne wherewith the Land is juſtly charged, and whereof I wiſh it were diſcharged. God is never well pleaſed with too much Cruelty. It may many ways be committed, and that againſt beaſt and man, ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and others, but eſpecially a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe that fear God, and his Miniſters. Againſt</p>
               <p n="1">1. Dumbe beaſts or Creatures without reaſon, we little thinke it; But the firſt words of the Angell to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:52979:26"/>the unmercifull Prophet <hi>Numb.</hi> 22.32. <hi>Wherefore haſt thou ſmittten thine aſſe?</hi> doe plainly ſhew that God ſhall call us to an account, for the unkind and cruell uſages of his poore mute Creatures. He hath made us Lords over them, not Tyrants; Owners, not Tormentors: He hath given us leave to kill them for our uſe, not to abuſe them at our pleaſure. They are ſo our drudges, that they are our fellowes by Creation. A righteous man ſaith <hi>Solomon Prov.</hi> 12.10. <hi>regardeth the life of his Beaſt;</hi> The Beaſt is to be fed according to his labour, and laboured according to his ſtrength, and in both his life is regarded; he doth not overworke him, and affords him good keeping. God who ſaveth man and beaſt <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.7. hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded they ſhould reſt from their toile <hi>on the Sabbath Day, Deut.</hi> 5.14. See alſo <hi>Chap.</hi> 22.6. how God provides for Birds.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly. Secondly, cruelty againſt man either 1. Condemned <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.2.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:52979:27"/>To one vvhoſe offence vvas not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall Forty Stripes vvere only to be given, and not aboue, to dravve our cruell rage, and fierce affections to pitty and compaſſion, Cruelty in deeds, or bitter vvords, even tovvard evill doers, that are already adjudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or ſtand at the Bar to be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is barbarous and inhumane. To inſult over a poore priſoner, or a condemned perſon, carried to the place of execution, ſtandeth neither vvith a humane diſpoſition, nor vvith a Chriſtian affection, or brotherly Compaſſion. Yet hovv common novv a dayes is this cruelty, even in, and at the place of Juſtice and Judgment, from vvhence all gall and bitterneſs ſhould be baniſhed.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly. Cruelty againſt our Brother vvho is at liberty, free, and his ovvn man.</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Levit.</hi> 24.19, 20. <hi>If a man cauſe any blemiſh in his neighbour, as he hath done ſo ſhall it be done to him, breach for breach, eye for eye, tooth
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:52979:27"/>for tooth,</hi> ſuch a blemiſh as he hath made in any, even ſuch ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paid to him; If then any fight with, or beat, or maim his Neighbour, he is cruell.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly. If by any meanes you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the death of your Neighbour, whether it be by ſword, famine, poyſon, falſe-accuſation, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, you are cruell, and for it to be rang'd with <hi>Cain who roſe againſt his Brother and ſlew him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3ly. If you play upon your Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours infirmities, making him your laughing-ſtock, or ſubject of your mirth and ſport; theſe deſerve pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ſhould move us to thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſs: It is but an unhappy wit that maketh ſport of anothers mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery. It is a kind of perſecution which ariſeth of contempt of our Brother, and a degree of murther <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.22. <hi>He that ſaith</hi> Raca <hi>to his Brother is guilty of a Councill. Raca</hi> ſignifieth all ſignes and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures that expreſs contempt, as
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:52979:28"/>ſnuffing, tuſhing, jeering. The Children of <hi>Bethel</hi> mocke <hi>Eliſha</hi> the Prophet.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. For his perſon, calling him <hi>bald pate.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2, For the favour of God ſhewed upon <hi>Elias</hi> his maſter, in ſaying <hi>aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend bald pate</hi> as thy maſter <hi>Elias</hi> did. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> 2. <hi>Kings</hi> 2.23.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="4">4ly. Moleſting widowes, or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs, <hi>Zach.</hi> 7.10. <hi>Oppreſs not the Widow,</hi> break not over where the he dge is loweſt, doe no wrong there eſpecially, where we have moſt eaſe and advantage to do it, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their weakneſs, and inability to ſave themſelves harmleſs, or to reſiſt and offend us. Therefore God in his Law gives charge ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and takes ſo great care of them <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.21.22. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.17.23. <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.28. <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.18. whoſoever moleſts widowes and fatherleſſe Children, is cruell in a ſpeciall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:52979:28"/>
               <p>Fifthly, if you injure ſtrangers you are cruell <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.21. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt neither vex a ſtranger nor oppreſſe him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod, <hi>22.21.</hi> Stangers.</note> a word ſignifying to make a ſpoil &amp; prey, to oppreſſe by might and violence, applyed uſually to the rich and mighty, that vex and ſpoil the poor, fatherleſſe, &amp; ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, whom God loveth, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth us to love, even as our ſelves, <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.18. <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.33.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.18.</note> 
                  <hi>If a ſtranger ſojourn with you in your Land, you ſhall not vex him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.33.</note> Verſ. 34. <hi>The ſtranger that dwelleth with you ſhall be as one borne amongſt you, and thou ſhalt love him as thy ſelf,</hi> Jer. 22.3. Do no wrong,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 22.3.</note> do no violence to the ſtranger who is moſt expoſed to wrong, ſuch there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath God taken into his more ſpeciall protection, <hi>Zach.</hi> 7.10.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixthly, if you wrong the poor,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach.</hi> 7. to.</note> one of theſe four wayes: Either.</p>
               <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Cruelty againſt tho poor.</note> Lending him money upon u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury; <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.25. <hi>If thou lend mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to any of my people that is poor
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:52979:29"/>by thee thou ſhalt not be to him as an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurer, neither ſhalt thou lay upon him biting uſury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, we are cruell to the poor, if we pay not the labourer his hire <hi>Deut.</hi> 24.14. <hi>Thou ſhalt not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe a needy, and poor hired ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant: thou ſhalt give him his hire for the day, the Sun ſhall not go down upon it, for he is poor, and therewith ſuſtaineth his life: Lest he cry againſt thee to the Lord, and it be ſin unto thee: See alſo</hi> Lev. 19.13. Deut 24.14. Of this <hi>Job</hi> 7.2. A Hireling looketh for his work, that is for the reward of his work. By <hi>Jeremy Jer.</hi> 22.13. A woe is proclaimed againſt ſuch oppreſſors, wo unto him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That uſeth his neighbours ſervice for nought, and giveth him not his work, that is, his wages, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.4. Behold the hire of the labourers, which is by you fraudulently kept back cryeth. Chriſt amongſt other weighty Laws nameth this for one, <hi>Mar.</hi> 10.19.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:52979:29"/>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, we are cruel to the poor, if we reſtore not the pledge of the poor, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.26. <hi>If thou takeſt thy neighbours raiment to pledge, thou ſhalt reſtore it to him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Sun go down.</hi> Obſerve that by raiment is meant.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That, which either he weareth by day, or lyeth in by night: under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand alſo</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, by proportion all other things, whereof he hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent uſe, as tools and inſtruments to work with, and ſuch like. But things neceſſary for to feed the life, as the Mill-ſtone which grindeth Corn, or any the like may not be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to pawn, <hi>Deut.</hi> 24.6. The Mill-ſtones are named but for an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance forbidding all others of like ſort, as pots which they boyl Meat in, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Fourthly, we are cruel to the poor, if we withdraw our Corn from them, <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.26. Hee that withdraweth Corn the people will
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:52979:30"/>curſe him; he who withholdeth Corn, holdeth as it were the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious hand of God, yea puts it back by his covetouſneſſe, when God in bounty hath ſtretched it forth to a Land: and therefore by diminiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing plenty to the people, they moſt juſtly pull down upon themſelves the curſe of the people. But he that ſelleth Corn lengthneth as it were the reach of Gods arme, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largeth his bounty ſent unto a Country. Wherefore the prayers of the people ſhall fetch down a bleſſing upon his head from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Now what is ſaid of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryman concerning his Corn, let the Citizen alſo mark concerning his wares. <hi>Non vincat honeſtatem utilitas, ſed honeſtas utilitatem.</hi> Let not profit overcome honeſty, but let honeſty overcome profit.</p>
               <p>Seaventhly and laſtly,<note place="margin">7ly.</note> cruelty may be uſed and exerciſed, by thoſe that are in any place of authority; even a petty Conſtable and Tything man,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:52979:30"/>eſpecially if he conceive himſelf in favour, with ſome he or ſhe great one, then where the ſheeps-ſkin will not ſerve, the Foxes muſt ſupply, and if that be diſcovered, then is he as a roaring Lyon and a raging Bear, <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.15. The right which he pleadeth is nothing but his Office; the mercy which he ſheweth, is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly where he cannot exerciſe more cruelty; the help which he affordeth is to expect worſe uſage. The miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief of wickedneſſe is great where it is joyned with power.</p>
               <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">3ly.</note> The third provoking ſin is Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty exerciſed againſt his immediate ſervants, his Saints and Miniſters, onely under that notion; If God be provoked with theſe and the like cruelties againſt beaſts and ordinary men, how greatly is he incenſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that cruelty which is exerciſed againſt his immediate ſervants, his ſaints, the righteous and upright in the Land, who walk uprightly with God and Man, not turning to the right
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:52979:31"/>hand nor to the left; who ſhew their holyneſſe by their upright and juſt dealing, not in mimicall geſtures and words. Yet there are ſome worſe then infidels even next to Devils, who hate all thoſe in whom they ſee the leaſt goodneſſe, even for their vertues and graces, ſuch they moſt diſlike, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, traduce, ſhun, and avoid; keeping company with any other, though never ſo vile, but ſtand in direct oppoſition to the Godly. The Heathens after Chriſts time did cry out againſt his followers. Chriſtians were the cauſes of all publike plagues and calamities. If <hi>Nilus</hi> did not overflow the field, if the Heavens ſtaid, the Earth quaked, if famine encreaſed, by and by the poor Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are caſt to the Lyons. But his Miniſters they are the thornes in the ſides of many now a dayes; they are accounted the ſcum and off-ſcouring of the World; their Meſſage and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons alike ſpitefully rejected, by men of an Anabaptiſticall ſpirit, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:52979:31"/>never found or felt their ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall miſery, dream nothing but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and conceive themſelves not to ſtand in need of them. Carry he himſelf never ſo peaceably &amp; meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, even to the looſing of the halfe of his livelihood, having no dealing with any in the matters of the World; I ſpeak by experience; Yet he is a man of ſtrife, &amp; a man of contention, whom every one curſeth, <hi>Jer.</hi> 15.10. If we threaten we are cruel Law preachers; if wee promiſe, we ſlatter; if mild, we are fearfull, and ſo deſpiſed and trampled on by every unworthy Aſſe; If bold we rail: prove we by argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments undeniable, we wreſt Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and are Sophiſters. Our aſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility is lightneſſe, our auſterity mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: Nothing can pleaſe them, who reſolve not to be pleaſed. Harveſt is done, the reapers muſt be diſcharged, and as for the time to come, we will have ſuch as will be contented with handfulls of barly &amp; peeces of bread, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.19. This ſome hope for,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:52979:32"/>who I hope will miſſe their hope. But no marvell, the quality and matter of their doctrine is ſo oppoſite to mans corrupt nature, that there upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperated to enmity againſt it ſelf, and the publiſhers thereof. There goeth beſides with their Miniſtery a kind of gall and wormewood to men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reformed. The two edged ſword in their mouth ſearcheth to the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the moſt hidden, and beſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved corruptions. Hence <hi>Elias</hi> by his doctrine troubles <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.17. Paul <hi>is accuſed by</hi> Tertullus <hi>to be a peſtilent fellow, and mover of ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> Chriſt himſelf the great Doctor of the world, is accounted a Sorcerer, Samaritane, drunkard, glutton, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver, divel, an Enemy to Caeſar, and a troubler of the publike peace. It muſt needs be very good, which Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan and his inſtruments hate and perſecute ſo much.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth grand ſin provoking God to wrath, is the Contempt of his Word: God hath made this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:52979:32"/>with any Nation, who will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him for their God, that if they will hear his voice indeed, and keep his covenant, then they ſhall be his chief treaſure above all people, a Kingdome of Prieſts and a holy Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>But how did his people of old keep his and their Covenant? They took no heed at all to this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, Law, or word of the Lord, but accounted it as a matter of no conſequence. Every one followed that way he liked beſt; Somtimes they heard it more for a Cuſtom, then any purpoſe to amend things amiſs; Wherefore the Lord grieved, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he gave them his word. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly in vain made he it, his Law, the pen of the Scribes is in vaine, as if be ſhould ſay, the Law is enacted in vaine, and by appointment of God put in writing by Scribes thereunto aſſigned for the uſe of his people, in regard of any uſe they made of it, or benefit that thence redounded to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:52979:33"/>them by it, becauſe it was by them no whit regarded, <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.8. And by his Prophet <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.2. <hi>I have ſtretched out my hand all the day unto a rebellious people, which walked ſtill in a way that was not good.</hi> God did la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour from time to time to reclaime them, and to reduce them to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of his word, and covenant he had made with them, but in vaine; they followed not the motions and directions of the word, and ſpirit, but their own mind and luſt. Therefore now he was fullie reſolved to reject them, as not his children, but the ſeed of the Adulterer, and of the Whore. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57. that is, not begotten by his word and ſpirit; but ſuch as forſooke God, their rather had Satan for their father; Thus they of old, and are we better? Is not the vvord diſeſteemed by moſt, as nor worth the hearing, but only that the Law and cuſtome is ſo. Doe not men in the generall proclaim it openly in their practices, that they will not be controuled, but
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:52979:33"/>doe as they ſee beſt. Are not men in wordly matters witty, and of great apprehenſion and judgment, yet as blind as beetles, and very blocks in religion? Eyes they have, and ſee not the things belonging to their peace; as bats and owls ſee beſt in the night, ſo their beſt underſtanding is of wordly matters. As a mole is nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and quick within the ground, but above ground can make little ſhift; ſo talke or deale with theſe men of worldly matters, and they are cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, but ſpeak of religion, and you poſe them as with a ſtrang language. VVhat is the reaſon of all this, but becauſe the word is not regarded? Again, have we not others who goe another way to overthrow the word? The word they confeſs is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable and neceſſary to gather a Church, but not to continue it; To begin Faith, but when it is begun and begotten in us, we need not hear ſtill: we have faith already by the word of God, we ſhall not therefore
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:52979:34"/>need to frequent the preaching of it ſtill, we have that wrought in us, which the word is appointed to worke. May not we apply to theſe that in the <hi>Comick, faciunt nae intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendo, ut nihil intelligant?</hi> In ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves to have faith thus, have they any? Is not this under a colour of having faith, to ſcorne and deride the preaching of faith? the word begetteth us,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2.</note> and the ſame as food ſuſtaineth us; It is to the weake milke, and ſtronge meate to riper yeares: He never had faith by the word, that ſeeketh not the ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of it by the word. Have you faith? then ſeeke to encreaſe and continue it; which is done by the ſame meanes, that it is bred and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendred: This Peter teacheth in his firſt Epiſtle, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.23. where he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the word <hi>immortall ſeed</hi> to rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate us, and <hi>Chap</hi> 2.2. <hi>ſincere milke</hi> to nouriſh us. So that we have aſwell our growing, as our firſt birth by it, and therefore ſtand alwayes in need
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:52979:34"/>of the preaching of it. The end of preaching is,
<list>
                     <item>1. Not only to convert us, but continue us.</item>
                     <item>2ly. Not only to raiſe us up, but to uphold us.</item>
                     <item>3ly. Not only to beget us to faith, but alſo to ſtrengthen us in the faith.</item>
                     <item>4ly. Not only to give the firſt life to us, but to renew us after our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold ſlipps, and often infirmities. In this life we have not attained to perfection, we always lack ſomwhat, we ſtand ſtill in need of renewing and repairing <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.12 The cauſe ſtanding thus vvith us, can vve any vvay imagine to eſcape that like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, Let the Apoſtle decide the matter <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3. He makes you judges, hovv ſhal we eſcape? He doth not ſay, if we contemne ſecretly, or openly, but if we neglect; the careleſs neglect ſhall pull judgement on us; neither doth he ſay, ſo great a vvord, but ſo great a ſalvation. <hi>The Goſpel is the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of God unto ſalvation Rom.</hi> 1.16.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:52979:35"/>Theſe vvhich contemne it, contemne their ovvn ſalvation. Behold the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſers, ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas Acts</hi> 13.41, as your forefathers by deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the word, brought heavy judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and plagues upon themſelves, even ſo ſhall you: beſides this, by this deſpiſing of the word, you judge your ſelves unworthy of ſalvation. <hi>ver.</hi> 46. this your unbeleife and contempt of the Goſpel, ſpeakes you unworthy of eternall life, this your own fact judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth you not worthy.</item>
                     <item>5ly. And laſtly; Diviſions amongſt our ſelves, cauſe the Almighty to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into a <hi>controverſy with his people. Hoſ.</hi> 10.2. This is that which weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and lames us, and layes us open to the inſulting triumphs of our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The warre of the Church is the peace of heretiks; our diſcord is their muſick; our ruine their glory: Oh what a ſight is this? brethren ſtrive, while the enemy ſtands ſtill, and laughs, and triumphs. If we deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:52979:35"/>the griefe of our mother the Church, the languiſhing of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, the Extirpation of religion, the loſs of poſterity, the advantage of our adverſaries, which way could theſe be better effected then by our own diſſenſions. Only charity, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and a ſincere mind will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay theſe broiles, that being perſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to correct, &amp; reforme thoſe things wherein we have manifeſtly tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Signes generall and particular of Gods anger with a Church and Nation.</head>
               <p>IN all Gods proceedings to judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he is pleaſed to give warning; he ever leaves a latitude between his ſentence and the execution of the ſame, this is a ſpeciall mercy to give us warning: He might come and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver tell us, out of mercy he tells us of it, before he commeth. God never comes to a blow without a word, to an execution without a warning. Had
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:52979:36"/>not thoſe of the firſt World who pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed in the flood, a fair and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full warning, one hundred and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years, all the time <hi>Noah</hi> was buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that veſſell, which ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the World in the generall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.3. Before that moſt grievous Captivity of Iuda, and deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> by the <hi>Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians,</hi> the Lord gave manifeſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of his diſpleaſure, and indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: <hi>in Ezek.</hi> 8.4. <hi>Chap.</hi> 9.3. <hi>Chap.</hi> 10.18, 19. <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.23. Wee find the glory of God had forſaken the Temple, and was come to the midſt of the City, where it ſtood to make one trial more to ſe whether the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple would call him back by invocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and lively repentance. All which divers motions of the glory of God, what doe they elſe but evidence Gods diſpleaſure, and purpoſe to leave a people, and that his venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is at hand, when he begins to withdraw the moſt lively and ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble tokens of his preſence, from thoſe
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:52979:36"/>places where he was wont to ſhew himſelfe moſt familiarly? Laſtly, what fearfull, and prodigious ſignes of his wrath and indignation, went before their finall &amp; utter deſtruction by the Romans, recorded by <hi>Joſephus,</hi> a great man of their own, Eye-witneſs, and actor of that Tragedy. A blazing ſtar like a ſword, and a Comet for a whole year together; A light, in the night about the altar, and the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as clear as day; A Lamb brought forth in the Temple by an Oxe brought in to be ſacrificed; The Eaſt gate of the Inner Temple, of braſſe, ſo heavy that Twenty men could hardly ſhut it, opening of its ovvn accord; Stange ſights of iron char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots, and armed troopes in the aire compaſſing the City about. Yet their miſery of miſeryes did not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertake them, untill upon the day of Pentecoſt in the night; the Prieſts ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrating their holy rites, they heard firſt ſome motion or noiſe, then a voice ſaying, let us depart hence: af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:52979:37"/>vvhich they had not a day of comfort, nor a gratious looke from their God, but a fatall unparalleld deſtruction by the ſvvord of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> under <hi>Veſpatian</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and ſonne: vvithout the ſvvord, and civill diſſenſions; famine, and peſtilence vvithin. All vvhich plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhevves that vvhen God vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dravves the lively tokens of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, he is ſore diſpleaſed, and ruine is at hand. But let us ſee the ſignes of his diſpleaſure vvith us? peruſe the Chronicles of latter Centuries, and if you meet not vvith many you are blind: I ſhall cull out a fevv; After religious King <hi>Edward</hi> the VI. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe, did not the Lord threaten this land and Church, in and by <hi>Qu. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry?</hi> vvhoſe heart did not then faint and quaile vvithin him for the little hope that vvas left? vvas it any leſſe then deſolation hee did threaten in LXXXVIII by that ſame blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly ſo called invincible <hi>Armado?</hi> were not Church and State, as a fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:52979:37"/>ſnatch'd out of the fire of that helliſh Powder plot? I confeſſe theſe are mercyfull Terrors and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, becauſe turn'd off by mercy into mercies. But I pray, what meant the building of <hi>Iames</hi> Chappel by <hi>King James;</hi> and afterwards ſending his ſonne the late unfortunate <hi>King</hi> into <hi>Spaine,</hi> contrary to the advice of learned Divines and States-men at home, and Ambaſſadors from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad reſiding here, who were reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as men out of their little wit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe out of their eſtate, by Gods vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation of the Church in forreign parts. Did not the Lord play the Lion amongſt us, by ſuffering our ſinnes to prevaile to an unnaturall civill war, wherein father and ſonne imbrewed their hands in each others blood, brethren did butcher one the other; <hi>of all the Vials of the wrath of God</hi> powred down upon ſinners, it is one of the foreſt, when a man is fed with his own fleſh, and made drunke with his own bloud, as with ſweet
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:52979:38"/>wine <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.26. I conceive none will deny this to be a generall token of Gods vvrath with this whole nation. Again uſually before ſome great ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity good and vvorthy men are taken away;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 12.3.2, 3.</note> this is a fearfull preſage, (ſaith godly Dr. <hi>Gibbs</hi> now with God) that calamity is comming: Hence at all times the ſurviving godly have la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented the death of ſuch:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12.1.</note> as <hi>David, Help Lord, the righteous are failed amongſt the children of men Micah</hi> 7.1.2. <hi>Woe is me for I am like the ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Gatherings, and the Grapes of the Vintage, the good man is periſhed from the earth:</hi> the reaſon of this mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is rendred by <hi>Iſaiah</hi> Iſa. 57.1. <hi>The righteous periſh, and noe man conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it in heart, and mercifull men are taken away and no man underſtandeth that the righteous is taken away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the evill to come.</hi> their death preſageth an evil to come. You will ſay it is a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy for them to be taken away from evill; but what hurt commeth to us? Let <hi>Ioaſh</hi> a great wicked one, becauſe
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:52979:38"/>a wicked King ſhew the reaſon in his Lamentation over old <hi>Eliſha</hi> now departing 2 Kings 13.14. <hi>O my father, my father,</hi> the Charet of Iſrael, and the horſemen thereof. They are the pillars of the Church, and the Strength of the Weale pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, they are thoſe who make good both places and time wherein they live, they keepe away evill, and doe good by example and prayers. <hi>Iob.</hi> 22.30. the innocent ſhall deliver the Iland; the good man delivers his neighbours amongſt whom he liveth by his prayers: or it may be read he ſhall deliver him that is not innocent a good man by his prayers ſometimes turnes away Gods judgments from the ungodly. We ſee how farre <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> prevayled with God for <hi>Sodom Gen.</hi> 18.32. Alſo <hi>Moſes</hi> for a whole ſinfull nation <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.11. to <hi>ver.</hi> 14. A good man is Gods favorite, ſee <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.1. What he will doe for the ſame, even ſpare the whole City. It is alſo a ſigne of Gods anger with a
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:52979:39"/>nation, when he ſuffereth the Church in the ſame to be corrupted either in purity, corrupting the doctrine with hereſy. All politicians hold this as a ſigne of a Churches, and Lands fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, vvhen the old Enemyes of truth encreaſe: Or vvhen the worſhip or ſervice is corrupted by Idolaters and Schiſmatikes, who by diviſion break the unity, which is a preſerver, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention in judgment will ſoone come to diſſention in affection, and ruine vvill be the end Hoſ: 10.2. Their heart is divided, their accord is gone, that cord is untwiſted, they cannot ſtand; As ſoon as men divide from God, he takes avvay his ſpirit; for he is the ſpirit of peace and concord: and then they give themſelves to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, and factions, never conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vvith any preſent ſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, till they have ruined all, and themſelves vvith it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:52979:39"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> The meanes to recall God, from depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing further from us, and to keepe him ſtill with us.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THe firſt is fruitfullnes. Is God provoked with our barrenneſs, and begins to depart from us, then certainely fruitfullneſſe vvill keepe him vvith us, and ſtay him from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting further: fruitfullneſs in good vvorkes muſt make amends for our former barrenneſs, not one fruit or the other, or one good vvorke, or as many as may be numbred (as many content themſelves vvith, and anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipate their revvard by glorying all their life time in one good vvork or the other) but as our bad fruites, our ſinnes, are without number, ſo much more muſt our good fruites be numberleſs. In fruitfullneſs is a fullneſs.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Fullneſs of Duty, or Dutifull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</item>
                  <item>2. Fullneſs of ſhame, for our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:52979:40"/>barrenneſs: that is ſhamefull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</item>
                  <item>3. Fullneſs of care, or carefullnes for our former negligence.</item>
                  <item>4. Fullneſs of pitty, or pittyfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for our former harſhneſs.</item>
                  <item>5. Fullneſs of mercy, or mercyfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for our former unmercifullneſs.</item>
                  <item>6. Fullnes of joy, or joyfullneſs for Gods ſparing us.</item>
                  <item>7. Fullneſs of thanks, or thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſs for loading us notvvithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our unvvorthineſs, vvith the choiceſt of his mercies and favours. It is obſervable in the Scripture, that the Children of women long barren proved moſt famous and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Of <hi>Sarah, Iſaac</hi> from whoſe loynes were multitudes deduced.</item>
                  <item>2. Of <hi>Rachel, Joſeph,</hi> that wonder of men and Angells.</item>
                  <item>3. Of <hi>Hannah, Samuel,</hi> that great Prophet and Prieſt of the Lord.</item>
                  <item>4. Of <hi>Elizabeth, John</hi> the Baptiſt of whom the Lord himſelf teſtifieth,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:52979:40"/>among them that are born of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.11.</note> there hath not riſen a greater. So theſe Saints that have been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of ſpirituall barrenneſs, and converted from a ſinfull life have proved moſt notable inſtruments of God glory. As</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Mary Magdalene,</hi> the receptacle once of Seaven divels, after ſhe was freed from them, had the honour to be the firſt Meſſenger of Chriſts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, and to have her memory propogated with the glorious goſpel <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.13.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly. <hi>Zacheus</hi> a publican, an extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting publican, yet how gratious was he to Chriſt? yea how gratious was Chriſt to him? <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.</p>
               <p n="3">3ly <hi>Paul</hi> born out of due time, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.8. yet outſtript the reſt, and <hi>was in labours more abundant then they all, verſ.</hi> 10. Thus the laſt have been the beſt, as the laſt grapes make ſweeteſt wine. It is fruitfullneſs the Lord lookes for, the ſame muſt be anſwerable to our former vanities.</p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:52979:41"/>
               <p n="4">4ly. Adde to the former Converts <hi>Manaſſes</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33.6.</p>
               <p n="5">5ly. Holy <hi>Auguſtine</hi> a great ſinner firſt wrote after his converſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> twelve books of repentance. <hi>Is Sion</hi> (the Church) his Vineyard, the ſame muſt be fruitfull? Is the Church his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, he goes thither to gather fruites <hi>Can.</hi> 6.11. Are we the ſpouſe of Chriſt, wee muſt be fruitfull for we are mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to Chriſt, that we ſhould bring forth fruit unto God <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.4. But what are theſe fruites? <hi>Gal,</hi> 5.22. <hi>Love, Peace, Joy &amp;c.</hi> Let us with dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diligence endeavour to redeeme our former barrennes, that ſo the Lord our God may continue with us.</p>
               <p n="2">2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. A ſecond means to keep God with us, and his bleſſing, is to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge Gods ſuperlative mercy in gathering and ſetling a Church here, paſſing by the greateſt part of the World, &amp; leaving them Aliens from the covenant without any hope, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12. We might have pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed in ignorance &amp; blindneſſe.
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:52979:41"/>This hath been the practice of Gods Children.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It was the bleſſing that <hi>Noah</hi> gave to his Son <hi>Iapheth</hi> for his dutifullneſs, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.27. God perſwade <hi>Iapheth</hi> to dwell in the Tents of <hi>Shem,</hi> that is, to be united with the Churches of the Jews, the poſterity of <hi>Shem,</hi> which was fullfilled when the Gentiles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came joynt heirs, and of the ſame body, and joynt Partakers of Gods promiſe in Chriſt by the Goſpel, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.6. <hi>The partition wall being broken down Chap.</hi> 2.24. They became fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Citizens with the Saints, and of the houſehold of God; and were no more ſtrangers and forreigners <hi>Verſ.</hi> 19.</p>
               <p n="2">2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> became a great man in Egypt, might have made his Sons great alſo, amongſt infidels, but his chief care was, to adopt them into the true Church of God to be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of her bleſſings, <hi>Gen.</hi> 43.13.</p>
               <p n="3">3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. <hi>Moſes,</hi> Heb. 12.24. <hi>by faith when he was come to age</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. By in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:52979:42"/>of <hi>Stephen, Act.</hi> 7.23. <hi>Full forty years, refuſed to be called the ſon of</hi> Pharaohs <hi>Daughter, and choſe rather to ſuffer adverſity with the people of God.</hi> Whatſoever <hi>Moſes</hi> did being a Child yet when he comes to diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he refuſed to be called the Son of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Daughter &amp; had rather live in the Communion of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, then to be a Prince amongſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers. The expreſſion is ſingular, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, he looked off from.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The honours, riches, profits, pleaſures, that were appertaining to a Crown, from the pompe and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the World.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Hee looked off from the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and miſeries of Gods people, which he was to undergo with them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He looked to the recompence of reward future. Hee looks off from the reproach of Chriſt, which would be but for a ſeaſon; aſwell as the riches and treaſures, to that which would be everlaſting. Therefore ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is ſuch a great bleſſing to live
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:52979:42"/>in the ſociety of the faithfull, wee ought to be thankfull to God that he made us members of the Church. Be not like to many, who have lived &amp; died in the boſome of the Church, yet have never taſted of the bleſſings &amp; graces of the Church; like fiſhes in the Sea never taſting of the ſaltneſſe of it. This is the reaſon why many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the Church, becauſe they haue not taſted how ſweet the Lord is in the ſame. Seing that God gives more where he hath given much, let us praiſe him all the wayes we can diſcover. The manner of prayſing God is ſix fold.</p>
               <p n="1">1<hi rend="sup">ſt.</hi> In mind, when we bear in mind the favours of God. Thus David <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77.11. I will remember the works of the Lord, ſurely I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thy wonders of old. It was curſed unthankfulneſſe in <hi>Iſrael</hi> to make haſt to forget his works, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.13. What can hee remember, that forgets the mercies of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. When we erect monuments,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:52979:43"/>pillars, and Trophies to continue the memory of Gods mercies. This ſhall be writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to come. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 102.18. Thus Jacob reared an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar: <hi>Gen.</hi> 33.20. to be a dumbe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſme to poſteritie, or a gratefull memoriall of Gods favour in giving him power not only to prevaile with himſelf for a bleſſing; but with his Brother <hi>Eſau</hi> to divert deſtruction.</p>
               <p n="3">3ly. When we praiſe God upon inſtruments <hi>Pſal.</hi> 150.</p>
               <p n="4">4ly. When we praiſe God with our hearts, this enlivens all the reſt, if it come out of a pure heart. Bleſs the Lord all that is within me, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.1. <hi>All that is within me,</hi> and all that is without me, but eſpecially all that is within me, bleſs the Lord O my ſoule. He loves little that can tell how much he loves.</p>
               <p n="5">5ly. When we praiſe God with our lips or tongues <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35.28. <hi>My tongue ſhall ſpeake of thy righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and of thy praiſe all the day long.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6ly. VVhen our lives praiſe God
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:52979:43"/>1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Let our converſation be honeſt, that they beholding your good workes may glorify God in the day of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſitation. Noli gloriari, quia lingua &amp;c.</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> never ſay you praiſe God with your words, when you diſpraiſe him with your workes.</p>
               <p>A third thing we muſt doe if we vvill ſtay the Lord, and keepe him vvith us, is to pray for the Church, and to doe all vve can to keepe the ſame amongſt us, I have made it plaine; That all vvhich God hath done vvas firſt for himſelf, next for his Church. Now vvill God conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue that amongſt us, which we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard not? Remember that in <hi>Hag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gai</hi> 1.4, Is it time for you to dwell in ſeeled houſes, whileſt Gods houſe lieth in the duſt; a ſharp pointed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe. O yee filly wormes, ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full wretches, ſo lately, and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly delivered to delight your ſelves in your ſeeled houſes, your graunges pallaces, and to be ſoe ungratefull to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:52979:44"/>your God, as not to let him have his owne houſe: doe you not only ſeeke neceſſaries, but alſo your pleaſures before Gods honour. Did God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the materiall houſe ſo much? No it was for their ſakes who did meet in it to praiſe the Lord. I doe not-deny but it is a great bleſſing the Lord affords us in giving us ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall publike houſes, which we call Churches, from the Greeke <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> as it were the Lords houſe; which ſome corrupted in mind, or yeelding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be abuſed ſo far by Popiſh Antichriſtian Emiſſaries, as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy thoſe places of publick worſhip, that men might be driven into cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to their no ſmall advantage, as the Apoſtle imtimateth 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6. by creeping into houſes they worke cloſely in corners, which openly they dare not adventer upon in our pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like oratories. Pray then with the Church, we muſt with David <hi>Pſ.</hi> 122.6. <hi>Pray for the peace of Jeruſalem,</hi> that is the Church of God, the whole
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:52979:44"/>Church, and every part and portion of the ſame, every branch and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber through the world, more ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally thoſe members that are emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, not in outward profeſſion of religion, and Chriſtian name, but thoſe that are really ſuch, eminent in place, worth and ſervice, ſingular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we are to pray for our own Church which we have relation to, and the Principalls of it, Cities alſo and Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities, and Schooles Seminaries of the Church, for thoſe now in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, for the Common good, and ſo the Churches alſo, that God would ſtrengthen and enable them againſt all oppoſition they are like to meet with; for all that labour for the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement of Chriſt meet with oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from Satan &amp; his Inſtruments, &amp; are tormented by them. Neither are we to pray alone for Jeruſalem myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall, but alſo for Jeruſalem literall, the converſion of the Jewes, <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.13. <hi>Returne, returne O Shunamite;</hi> an earneſt invitation and perſwaſion
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:52979:45"/>which the Church of the Gentiles makes to the Jewiſh Synagogue to come off from her former worſhip and adminiſtrations to the Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Covenant, that ſo both may be made one in that fullneſs and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, this is promiſed <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.25. and not yet fulfilled, therefore it is our dutie to pray for it. And as we are to pray for Jeruſalem the Church, ſo likewiſe collaterally againſt all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of the Church, for it is with the Church and her enemies, as it is with a paire of ballances, when one ſcale goeth up the other goeth down ſo that thoſe prayers that are made for the Church directly, reach collate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally againſt her enemies.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Queſt.</note>But what is the thing we muſt wiſh, or pray for in behalfe of the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſ.</note>Dauid calls it peace in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quoted place which according to the Hebrew phraſe comprehendeth in his lap all good things; protection of the Church, freedome of thoſe
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:52979:45"/>who are in dangers, preſervation of thoſe who are out of it. That God would reſtore thoſe that are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runne, refine and purge them which remaine: That God would enlarge the borders of Chriſts Kingdome and adde dayly to the Church ſuch as ſhall be ſaved. But more properly if we conſider, the peace we are to pray is threefold.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Peace with God, to cauſe his Churches to walke in the puritie and power of his ordinances; to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine true religion in doctrine and worſhip, which being left, all other things muſt needs decay. Tamper with that and all other bleſſings will be gon, they will betake themſelves to their wings, and fly away; Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we keepe our peace with God, all other peace will fall aſunder.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We pray alſo that we may be at peace amongſt our ſelves, enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing civill peace, free from diſſention, diviſions, and diſtraction, that all thinke the ſame thing, goe the ſame
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:52979:46"/>way, and all unanimouſly minde the glory of God.</p>
               <p n="3">3ly, We underſtand alſo peace for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine, from all oppoſition from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, that there may be no hoſtilitie, no invaſion of forrain enemies upon the Churches of God, and our Church ſpecially. One thing more by way of Caution, and that is, if we dreame of temporall peace only, and the bleſſings upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that, it is not worth the while to pray for the peace to the Churches of God, It may better proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in warre and miſery. The primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church as long as it was perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by the Dragon, was clothed with the ſunne, crowned with a Crown of twelve Stars, having the moone under her feet, ſhee contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth worldly things, But that wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Chap. 17. is all cloathed in ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, and gold, outwardly rich, poore and beggarly within; we muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore pray for a ſanctified peace, and that we may make good uſe of it. I had almoſt forgotten that which
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:52979:46"/>
                  <hi>David</hi> remembreth in his 51 <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 18. <hi>That God would build the walls of Jeruſalem,</hi> walls are fences againſt enemies; the Churches walls are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline and order; this is that hedge keepes out the wild beaſt out of the Lords vineyard, late experience hath made it good; I will ſay nothing but as that <hi>Roman Emperour; ſi diſcipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam amittimus, nomen Romanum amittimus,</hi> and as it is in an Army and Commonwealth, ſo we dayly find it in the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Motives to pray for the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. In Generall; There cannot be a better imployment for Chriſtians then prayer, and we cannot ayme at a better bleſſing, then a ſanctified peace and ſettlement both of Church and State. There is not a neerer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation we have to any for whom we ſhould wiſh all good then the Church. The neereſt relation that a Chriſtian hath to any for whom he ſhould wiſh good, is the Church, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt bleſſing is a good peace and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement;
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:52979:47"/>The moſt effectuall meanes to attaine this, is fervent prayer.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He that loves the Church will pray for her, it is a moſt certain ſigne, we doe not love the Church, nor Gods glory, if we will not ſo much as pray for her, even then when o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſeeke her ruine.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Our prayers for the Church give us a ſhare in all the Churches pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, no prayers, no ſhare.</p>
               <p n="4">4. All our proſperity depends on the proſperity of the Church, all the good that God doth is for the Churches ſake. Out of Sion God bleſſeth, and true proſperity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth onely to ſuch as love the Church. The Church I have ſhewed is.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Gods houſe, the ſpouſe of Chriſt, and can there be a neerer and dearer relation to a Chriſtian then this, to tender the houſe of God, and ſpouſe of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Church, if we be true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, is the Mother of us all, all
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:52979:47"/>ſaints Sons and Daughters,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 4 26.</note> have the Church for their Mother: whoſoever denies her, denies alſo God to be his or her Father; In her we are born, in her we are new born: He is an unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Son, and ſhe an unnaturall Daughter, who will not pray hard for her Mother in danger, who will not open their mouth to keep harme from their Mother.</p>
               <p n="5">5<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. Such is the efficacy of fervent prayer that it ſtayes the hand of the Almighty, and (with greateſt reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence be it ſpoken to the divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty) in a manner binds the ſame: Prayers rule God. <hi>Let me alone</hi> ſaith, God to Moſes, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.10. The prayers of the faithfull ſtay his pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, not by the prevayling of humane force above divine, but by condeſcending of divine grace to the deſires of the Godly. By prayer we obtain all things of God, whatſoever Gods divine power is able to bring to paſſe, a Godly Chriſtain may obtain by his fervent prayer.</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:52979:48"/>
               <p n="6">6<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. We muſt of neceſſity pray, if we will obtain; Look for no bleſſing of God without prayer, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.11. Thou ſhalt call on me.</p>
               <p n="7">7<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. In praying for the Church, you pray for your ſelves, if you be a live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly member of the ſame.</p>
               <p>By theſe motives you may eaſily find of what temper and mould you are off, that ſhall read this; all pretend to Chriſtianity, and to be members of Chriſt, now try the truth of this by your affection to the Church. The Church is Chriſts body; He is the head, you and others, if believers are members; If ſo then you feel, are ſenſible of the breaches made in this body: can a rupture, can a breach be made in a body, and a true lively member of the ſame not be ſenſible? It is a dead member that hath loſt feeling, or at leaſt benummed and ſtupified for the preſent; whatſoever you have done hitherto, yet now remember your duty to pray for the welfare of your Mother the Church;
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:52979:48"/>obſerve the ſad eſtate of the ſame: what the eye ſees the heart will mind: If we do not minde the Church, we will never carefully make our expreſſions to God for her. Take heed of the World, which like Ivy will claſp about your heart, and hinder it from thriving in Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; Be not like that Canniball of Chriſtians, even the beſt Proteſtants, bloudy <hi>Alva,</hi> who when <hi>Henry</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of him, whether he had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of the great Eclips? Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, he was ſo much taken up with matters on earth, that he had no lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to mind heavenly things. I fear wee have too many ſuch amongſt our Common Chriſtians, who whilſt heaven and earth are on fire about their ears, and the Church in ruine, and themſelves in danger, yet like the <hi>Syracuſan Archimedes,</hi> they are in the duſt, minding nothing but earth: what is the Church to them, let Churchmen imploy their time this way. Such I would have to conſider
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:52979:49"/>the words of <hi>Mordecai</hi> to Queen <hi>Heſter.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heſt.</hi> 4.14.</note> If thou altogether holdeſt thy peace at this time, then ſhall the Churches enlargement and deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance ariſe from another place, but you and your Fathers houſe ſhall be deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>To cloſe up all, do but conſider, that it is but almoſt the onely thing left us that we can do for the Church abroad, and our Brethren in the Jaws of Anti-Chriſt, to pray for them. It is an eaſy thing and of little coſt; none therefore may ſtick at it, to give his contribution of prayers and ſighs that way. If we neglect it, it will be a foul blot, we ſhall get as much cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit by calling our ſelves to be Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, Members of the Church, as Pilate hath gotten to be named in the Creed.</p>
               <p n="4">4<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> A fourth mean to keep God with us is to adde to Godlineſſe, Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly Kindneſſe, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.7. This is the Daughter of Godlineſſe. He that loves God for his own ſake, will love
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:52979:49"/>his Brother for Gods ſake. This is the touchſtone of piety. This is a demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration that we love God, and his Church, his ſpouſe, and our Mother, with one and the ſame love, we love God, and our Brother; the difference is in the degrees &amp; reſpects. God for himſelf, others for him and in him; I wiſh I might as truely write to you of this duty, as the Apoſtle 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.9. As touching brotherly love, we need not that I write unto you, for yee your ſelves are taught of God to love one another: Indeed ye do it towards all the Brethren which are in <hi>Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> (in other parts of Chriſtendome.) But we beſeech you Brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that you encreaſe more and more, as you are taught of God to love one another. It is a thing very unpleaſing to God for Brethren to be at variance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves. By natures light, though dimme, the very heathens have acknowledged one God, and him the Author of unity and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip <hi>Plato</hi> in his <hi>Lyſis;</hi> from the ſame
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:52979:50"/>parents, one Father, and one Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as from one ſeed, one root, one beginning by natures ordinance do ſpring two, three, or more Brethren; not for diſcord or contrariety, but that being many, they might the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter one help the other. That Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that warreth with his Brother, ſaith <hi>Plutarch,</hi> doth voluntarily cut off a member of his owne fleſh. All enmity breedeth within our ſoul a thouſand tormenting paſſions, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially that enmity which a man beareth towards his ovvn Brother, as that vvhich is moſt prodigious, and unnaturall. <hi>Xenophon.</hi> May not many novv a dayes complain vvith <hi>David.</hi> If mine enemy had done me this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour I could have born it,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.12.</note> if my adverſary had exalted himſelf againſt mee, I would have hid my ſelf from him; but it was thou, O man, my companion, my guide, my familiar; we walked in the houſe of God as friends. Of all the vialls of the wrath of God poured out upon ſinners, it
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:52979:50"/>is one of the foreſt to be fed with his own fleſh, and made drunk with his own bloud, as with ſweet Wine, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.26. When one ſhall deſtroy the other, and ſhed the blould of each other as eagerly and greedily, as if it were meat and drink to them, yea the moſt delightfull drink to them that could be, to be making havock off, and ſpilling the bloud either of other. But what will be the end of this? O the miſery of civill diſſenſions! I had rather mourn for this breach, then meddle with it. God knows how willingly would I ſpend life and all that little my good God hath bleſſed me with, for this earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paradiſe, or Canaan flowing with milke and honey, if it would avail any thing; But I well ſee that tears are fitter for this, then words; one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I beſeech you (not to lay open the evils, which have already come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us by the diſcord of Brethren, it would be over long, &amp; tedious,) note the chiefeſt evils of this enmity. It is</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:52979:51"/>
               <p n="1">1. A joy, and an encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the enemies of the Goſpel, our diſcord is their Muſick; oh what a ſight is this! Brethren ſtrive, While the enemy ſtands ſtill, laughs and triumphs; <hi>Bellum haereticorum, pax eſt Eccleſiae,</hi> ſayes <hi>Hilary</hi> of old; we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert it upon our ſelves, our war in the Church is the peace of hereticks. As it is in an army of men at deadly variance amongſt themſelves, the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe party againſt which they ſhould wholly together bend their forces, will ſay, we ſhall not need to do much, they will pull down and deſtroy themſelves; This is their joy.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The wounding of the weak is another great evil, ariſing from the diſcord eſpecially in religion, many if they are not caſt down, or turned out of the way, at leaſt wiſe are much hindred: would to God I could either deny this with truth, or amend it with tears; oh the wofull caſe! How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny do learn to fit their faith to the times, and are more impatient of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:52979:51"/>a remedy then of the diſeaſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Again. This diſcord brings con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to both parties, the Miniſters of the Goſpel eſpecially, which ſhould be had in precious account for their work ſake. The vulgar doth not diſtinguiſh between the ſubſtance of Religion and the Ceremony. But prayſed be God our differences are thoſe of <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> not thoſe of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Magus.</hi> Rome is cryed up for unity and peace; yet <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> a witneſſe without exception, acknowledgeth and reckoneth up 237. Contrarieties of Doctrine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Romiſh divines. But that which is worſt of all by diſcord.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The glorius Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt is diſgraced, in the diſgrace of men, the power of the Miniſtry is weakned, for where the teacher is deſpiſed the Doctrine is little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded.</p>
               <p n="5">5. A fifth meane to pleace God, &amp; ſtay him, is delivered by the Apoſtle 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Study to be quiet, and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:52979:52"/>meddle with your own buſines, and to worke with your own hands:</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſeeke after peace and quietneſs, with a kind of holy ambition (even as the ambitious forhonour,) thinking it our honour to live at peace. To calme our turbulent ſpirits, and to live at peace: we have here</p>
               <p n="1">1. the duty <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſtudy to be quiet.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Meanes availeable to performe it. Hither to turne the ſtreame of our ambition, and if we will needes bee judging, to vſe our judgement in this, not to put a ſtumbling block be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the weak <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.13. The qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et recommended unto us importeth not only peaceableneſs, and ſhunning contentions and vaine janglings, but a contented calme converſation, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to tumultuous turbulency, and reſtleſs intermeddling with things that concerne us not: as God hath diſtributed unto every one, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>ſo let him walk, and ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine I in all Churches:</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.17.</p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:52979:52"/>
               <p n="1">1. God hath ordained the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall places and callings.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly. He hath given gifts of abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to men to performe the things he requireth in the ſame.</p>
               <p n="3">3ly. He hath alſo ſet the bounds and limits within which every one is to keep himſelfe, and to walke order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, medling with that which apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth unto him: this is an holy thing and comely, a preſerver of unitie wherein God delights. A duty much to be endeavoured; in no age, or Church more neceſſary to be urged then our owne; abounding with ſo many buſie ſpirits, and reſtleſs male-contents. <hi>Athens</hi> it ſelfe was never ſo madde upon novelties as <hi>England</hi> now, whence it comes to paſs that ſome through their ambition to be ſingular, and popular, to draw diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples after them, have as it were gone down to hell for new faith and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall doctrines, not contented with the old. Churches in forraigne parts have complained of it, divers
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:52979:53"/>yeares agoe when things were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo bad in this reſpect, as ſince they have been, the <hi>Walachian</hi> Churches in an Epiſtle ſent to the <hi>Aſſembly of Divines at Weſtminſter,</hi> ſet forth the haynouſneſs of the crime. Let your conſcience judge ſay they) how all kind of hereſies can paſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed, manifold ſeeds of ſchiſmes be ſowne, and prophane doctrines of errors commonly vented abroad in that Citie, yea in that nation, which by ſo expreſs, ſacred, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere an oath hath bound it ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, to caſt out all errors, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and ſchiſmes from the houſe of God. I wiſh with all my heart, we had not made our ſelves a reproach amongſt Papiſts, and a ſcandall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the enemies of the Goſpel. But let the unſeduced conſider the judgement of Chriſt, &amp; his Apoſtles. Concerning ſuch novelliſts, Chriſt calls them <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.8. <hi>theeves and rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; ravening wolves in ſheeps cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Matth.</hi> 7.15. as if he ſhould ſay
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:52979:53"/>in appearance harmeleſs, but whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhews of good will they make, they ſeek to deſtroy your ſoules. The Ap. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.13. terms them deceiptfull workers becauſe whatſoever maſk of zeale they put upon them, as if they ſought nothing but Gods glory, yet indeed they ſought their owne gaine, and wrought upon advantage, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Bew are of Dogs</hi> that is falſe Apoſtles who barked at the light of truth, ſnarled and bit ſound and ſincere preachers, with their ſlanders <hi>Ezech.</hi> 13.4 foxes in dry places, that is in places where no poultry or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther birds are to feed upon; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon being hungerſtarved they gape after prey, and ſeiz upon the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt food, verſ. 19: handfulls of Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, any light reward, and peices of bread, <hi>Horum genus aliud domeſticum &amp; oceultum eſt, aliud externum &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtum; Illud vero longe nocentius, eorum inquam, qui in Eccleſia contra Eccleſiam ſentiunt, Hieron. Tom.</hi> 6. <hi>in Micah. cap.</hi> 6. Some of them are
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:52979:54"/>cloſe within our walls, others without and manifeſt: of the two thoſe are the dangereſt, who being in the Church ſpeak againſt the Church: have not we ſuch as the Apoſtle ſaith crept in, private perſons, which would ſeeme very religious, and to ſeek the holy unitie above others, which leave the dutie of their places and callings, and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie themſelves with thoſe matters which doe not belong to them, ſuch the Apoſtle commands.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To doe their owne buſineſs. And</p>
               <p n="2">2.ly. To work with their owne hands. Theſe are meanes availea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to preſerve unitie, quietneſs, and peace, cauſe the way of God, true religion to be well ſpoken of, and winne them that are without the truth, that is, unbeleevers, inſidels. Although ſuch in things ſpirituall know little or nothing, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. Yet have they written with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:52979:54"/>their hearts ſome naturall princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Law morall, by which they are directed to order their own Lives, and enabled to judge of other mens; but thoſe account the matters of their trades and ſciences, to which God by their inclination, diſpoſition naturall, and inſtruction of their Maſters hath called them, too baſe; or as if the Care of their familie were a thing over vile, they ſet theſe aſide and neglect them, and take upon them greater and higher buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. They labour not with their hands, nor meddle quietly with their owne buſineſs, but bind all the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers of their mind, to except againſt Church and State; As if God had made them to be overſeers of the Governours and Teachers, they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute and reaſon about Government, and the duties of Governours and Teachers, wandring about and ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to perſwade and draw others to their mind. But who hath given them power to diſpute with this rule
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:52979:55"/>of the Apoſtle. Let ſuch anſwere to the following particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Hath God called them, and ſet them on worke, about greater things and freed them from theſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Is there not labour, and paines and care to be taken in inſtructing their Children, and ſervants in the way of God? In providing earthly things, neceſſary for himſelf &amp; them <hi>leſt they deny the faith, and be worſe then Infidells.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Is not he more worthy blame that findeth fault with the greater, and doth it not in the leſſer. When the greater is more difficult to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme? To neglect his own little fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and his own defects, and to give himſelf in words and deeds to deprave the publike guides.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Is the truth obeyed, or God well pleaſed by ſuch wayes? When the Ruler &amp; guides of Gods people do amiſſe, a man is to be ſorry at it, &amp; he is to look to his own wayes that he keep upright before God. But
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:52979:55"/>when in reprehending that which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers fail in, hee neglecteth his own calling how ſhall he free himſelf from that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.1. Thou art therefore inexcuſable, O man, that judgeſt an other, for wherin thou judgeſt another thou condemneſt thy ſelf, for thou that judgeſt doſt the ſame thing; lament and ſorrow for evil, conſent not in any wiſe, follow the wayes of the Lord, obey the rules of the word; and let all men keep their place and ſtanding which God hath ſet them in, and ſo walke as that they may Anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>were before the high judge, and give account how they have diſcharged their duty.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Sixthly. If you would have God ſtay with you, and his bleſſings, ſeparate not from the Church his people, <hi>God bleſſeth out of Zion,</hi> If by the Miniſtry of the Goſpel God daily adds to his Church, member, ſociety &amp; externall communion of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſuch as ſhall be ſaved; then it is
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:52979:56"/>a dangerous ſymptome of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, who ſeparate from the Church: I ſhewed formely ſome of the priveleges of the Church, lo here an other dignity of it, There is no ſalvation out of it: it is like to Noahs Ark, for as in the World all pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed that were not gathered into the Ark, their wiſdome, Towns, Caſtles and goods could not ſave them, ſo all that are not gathered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church they ſhall periſh, the Church is the Ark of God there is no ſalvation but in Sion, that is the Church of God: therefore the holy Word ſaith, of thoſe God had a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to ſave, he added to the Church ſuch as ſhould be ſaved, and that from day to day he added them, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.23. It is ſaid that Chriſt is the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of his Body, now the Church is the Body of Chriſt, therefore there are none ſaved but the Church, that is none but they which are joyned to Chriſt the head, and become mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of him, hold therefore ſtill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:52979:56"/>with, it, and ſuffer not your ſelves to be drawn from the ſociety of it, <hi>John.</hi> 6.68. When many ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped away, Chriſt ſaid to the twelve, will ye alſo go away, Peter anſwered; <hi>Lord, to whom ſhall we go, thou haſt the Words of eternall life,</hi> when you ſee others to go out of the ſociety of the Church, ſay you, whither ſhall we go? Here are the Words of eternall life, here are the means to get faith and repentance, here are the means of ſalvation: remember what the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.9. <hi>Be not car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried about with divers and ſtrange Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, for it is a good thing that the heart be eſtabliſhed.</hi> As God hath up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held Religion among us ſtrangely, and miraculouſly doth yet, ſo let us hold it faſt and perſevere in it, to the end, Though an Angel from Heaven, much more though a Prieſt or Jeſuit from Rome, an Anabaptiſt, or a ſectary Preach unto us any other Goſpel, be carryed by none of them all: carry to Chriſt, be not carryed
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:52979:57"/>from Chriſt, take heed therefore of falſe Prophets.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Of falſe Teachers.</head>
               <p>THe ſtate of Chriſts Church mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant here on Earth, never hath been, nor is now, nor ever ſhall be ſo happy, as to bee free from falſe Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers; She cannot eſcape this grand evil, ſo long as there is a Sheeps skin to be gotten for a Wolf to maſke in: or a Sorcerer <hi>Elymas</hi> can uſurpe the name of <hi>Bar-Jeſus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 13.6.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe have been and will be, till Chriſt hath houſed all his friends, &amp; impriſoned all his enemies. This is a true Propheſy of a falſe Propheſy. But you demand what is falſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, &amp; who are the Teachers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of?<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Falſe Doctrine hath divers names in holy writ; according to the divers conditions of the ſame, ariſing from the Authors, matter, and degrees.</p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:52979:57"/>
               <p n="1">1. For firſt Chriſt calleth them <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.38. to 41. <hi>tares (Zizania)</hi> ſaith a learned man is blaſted Corne or deafe eares which grow up with the good corne, and cannot be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned from it untill the harveſt, and then it proveth naught. So will all falſe doctrine, though pleaſing now prove falſe in the end; together with all hypocrites <hi>verſ.</hi> 41. ſcandalls, which is the bridge in a trap, which when the mouſe or any other ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min puts downe they are taken; falſe doctrine then gives ſcandall, that is ſets a trap in our brothers way to take and deſtroy him.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly. The Apoſtle 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. calleth the ſame ſchiſmes or diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Falſe doctrines in a manner divide Chriſt and teare him in peeces by making him the head of two di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and diſagreeing bodies, himſelf being but one.</item>
                  <item>2. They divide themſelves from Chriſt by going to a falſe Chriſt.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:52979:58"/>
               <p n="3">3ly. They divide themſelves in heart to be found faultie <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 10.2. and <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. he ſtileth them conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or ſtrife. <hi>Boni Catholici, quod ad fidei doctrinam pertinet ita quaerunt, ut abſit decertatio periculoſa,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſt.</hi> Good Catholike Chriſtians do queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as that they avoid dangerous contending; But men of corrupt minds and deſtitute of the love of truth, contend not that error might be overcome of the truth, but that their ſayings may goe for currant, and other mens be put down, <hi>Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander-like</hi> they are ſo cold in cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, that they cannot live but in the fire of contention: out of it they are as it were dead, but if engaged in ſome contention then are they lively. This is the vvay to ruinate the Church, Altar againſt Altar, Profeſſor againſt Profeſſor, vvho getteth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by? Sathan, the Papiſts, to vvhom vve have given this ſtaffe to ſmite us vvith, namely our contentions. A grievous ſinne Companion of the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:52979:58"/>blackeſt iniquities <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.13.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.13 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3.</note> The marke of carnall men 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3. The doctrine then of falſe teach<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers is like themſelves, deceitfull making ſhew of good, and vvhole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome corne for food of the ſoule, but in truth it is blaſted and deafe; yea the ſame is full of danger, hiding traps to take and to deſtroy, divid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from Chriſt, yea Chriſt himſelf, and their ovvn hearts, to the ruine of the Church and themſelves.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly, If the doctrine be ſo deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and dangerous, vvhat are the teachers? The Scripture deſcribeth them alſo both in the old and new Teſtament. <hi>Ezkiel</hi> names them foxes chap. 13.4. Subtile, ravenous, of whom the ſpouſe complaineth 2. <hi>Cant.</hi> 15. that they <hi>Spoile her vines,</hi> that is members of the Church, the faithfull, the Churches. And that falſe prophets, or falſe teachers, are ſuch appeares by their fruits and natures having not only the craft of that beaſt transforming themſelves. 2.
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:52979:59"/>
                  <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.13. carrying a Fox in their boſome, when they are lambes out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly; but alſo the bloudy rage and crueltie, where they get power, none being like them: for never did the Church of God ſuffer more from the maddeſt and blindeſt heathen, then ſhe hath done from hereticks and ſchiſmaticks, that were among them. In the new Teſtament Chriſt calleth them theives and robbers, ſeeking to deſtroy, ſlay and kill <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.18, <hi>ravenous wolves verſ.</hi> 15. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> from <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to teare in pieces; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>rapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> ravenous, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.29. <hi>grievous wolves not ſparing the flock. Horum genus longae nocentius qui in Eccleſiâ contra Eccleſiam ſentiunt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Hieron.</hi> Farre more dangerous are they, who in the Church hold againſt the Church. Great danger is intimated by Chriſt, to be imminent to poore Chriſtians, from falſe teachers. They as wolves are of a bloudy nature, and their enmitie and crueltie to the ſheep is ſuch, that ſtrings made of
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:52979:59"/>both their guts, and joyned together in one muſicall inſtrument, wil never be conſonant; ſuch enmity and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary nature is between faithfull Chriſtians and falſe teachers. The wolfe invading the flock, never leaves till he have killed all. In like manner falſe teachers ſeeke to infect and deſtroy all.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8.</note> Like the divell their Father they goe up and downe like a roaring Lion ſeeking whom they may devour. Paul deſcribes them exactly <hi>Act.</hi> 20.29.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They are wolves, who both by their doctrines and manners, ſeek to deſtroy the harmeleſs and innocent ſheep.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly. Grievous they are and rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, by which their cruelty is noted, which is alſo explained by him in theſe words, <hi>not ſparing the flocke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3ly. Of our owne ſelves ſhall ſuch men ariſe, they ſhall not come from without, ſuch deceivers are the more langerous.</p>
               <p n="4">4ly. They ſhall ſpeake perverſe
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:52979:60"/>things, broaching falſe and hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call doctrines.</p>
               <p n="5">5ly. Ambition and pride ſhall cauſe this, to draw diſciples after them.</p>
               <p>Chriſt gives us two markes, by their Garments and fruites, not of life and manners, ſo much as of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.15.</p>
               <p n="1">1. What are thoſe ſheepes Cloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. In generall, by clothing whoſe uſe is to cover, we underſtand their cloſe comming in, their cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping into houſes, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6. Their chiefeſt care is to cover, hide and conceal at firſt, that which they chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intend to bring in.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Their good words and fair ſpeeches, by which they deceive the hearts of the ſimple. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, good words, when a man maketh ſhew of much goodneſſe, in words, but is nothing ſo in ſubſtance, and deed. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, many good prayers, and elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent counterfeit zeal, which here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:52979:60"/>and ſchiſmaticks uſe, to draw the ſimple to their ſide and opinions. Beware of ſuch ſugred and faire tongues, thus ſuch ſubtill Merchants do vent their bad wares, ſhew their errours not naked, but cloaked with good works, and fair ſpeeches.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.14.</note> Thus did the Phariſees under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of long prayer devour wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows houſes.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Their uſing or rather abuſing the Scripture, wreſting, corrupting, mayming, eluding the ſame, and thus with Satan the Arch-heretick they cover their errours. <hi>Sub nomine Chriſti, docent, quae contraria ſunt Chriſto, nec mirum ſi aliquos ſeduci videamus ah his, cum Dominus dixerit, multos ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent.</hi> Under the name of Chriſt, they teach things contrary to Chriſt, and ſhall we wonder to ſee ſome to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by them, when our Lord hath foretold they ſhall ſeduce many? <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom, Aliunde ſuadere non poſſent de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus fidei, niſi ex rebus fidei.</hi> Whence ſhould they perſwade matters of
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:52979:61"/>faith, if it were not out of thoſe wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of faith: ſaith <hi>Tertullian.</hi> Thus <hi>firmos fatigant, infirmos capiunt, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dios cum ſcrupulo dimittunt.</hi> They weary the ſtrong, take the weak, and the middle ſort they leave di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted with doubts.</p>
               <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5.</note> Fourthly, formality is meant by Sheeps cloathing <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; not the true forme and eſſence of Godlineſſe, but an outward confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, a reſemblance, vizard or ſhew of holyneſſe. All their outward car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage is ſo compoſed, as if they one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly were true Chriſtians, they profeſſe Religion, ſpeak well of God, of Chriſt, and diſcourſe well concerning out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward righteouſneſſe, and holyneſſe of life; that if all Religion were to be meaſured by the outſide, they could not chuſe but go for good Chriſtians. But what ſaith the Apoſtle of ſuch, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.16. <hi>They profeſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they know God, but in works they deny him,</hi> they expreſſe no ſuch things in their lives and converſations they
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:52979:61"/>have onely drawn a fair glove over a foul hand, ſuch were <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.28. And the Phariſees, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.27. <hi>They made clean the outſide;</hi> that is, Hypocrite-like, they made much adoe about Ceremonies and outward indifferent things, but for the inward, and moſt neceſſary parts of Gods worſhip they are very careles. The Apoſtle therefore in this place gives certain markes whereby we may try our own hearts and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, then others: It is a very hard thing to knovv a Hypocrite, being a lurking ſin, ſo maſked, as there is little, or no outvvard difference, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tvveen the ſound and unſound. They are very Divel-like, vvho dare range every profeſſor under this title, and marke him vvith the black cole of Hypocriſy. For though it be true that a Hypocrite muſt be a Profeſſor, yet it is falſe, that every Profeſſor muſt be a Hypocrite.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtles markes are.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They Profeſſe they knovv God;
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:52979:62"/>a Hypocryticall falſe Teacher, is a great Profeſſor of Religion, his care is to ſeem to be that he is not.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By works they deny him; all his Religion is in outward profeſſion, ſeparated from the inward ſincerity of the heart. That which God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights in, an humble and contrite ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, they regard not, and that which God deteſts they offer to him, a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked outward formality; he is ſwan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, white without, but his fleſh with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is black, Chriſts compariſon ſits them beſt, they are Foxes whoſe skin is better then his fleſh.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, diſobedient, or want of the obedience of faith: they make a great ſhew of faith, much know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, much talke of Piety, but ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly in their courſe depart from the word with pretence of obedience, like the Son in the Goſpel, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.28. Being bidden of his Father to <hi>go into the Vineyard,</hi> ſaid yea, but for all that went not, ſuch profeſſe much readineſſe and willingneſſe to ſerve God, but doe it not.</p>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:52979:62"/>
               <p n="4">4. Fourthly, The fourth marke is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, reprobate, not as oppoſed to the elect, but to thoſe things they undertake, as true Chriſtians, when they ſhall be brought to the touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, they ſhall be like reprobate ſilver, unaprooved, without proof, all naught.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The fifth thing meant by Sheeps-cloathing, is pretence of inſtinct, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations immediate, and extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary from the Spirit of God, <hi>Micah.</hi> 2.11. If a man walking in the Spirit, that is, ſay, he have divine inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet ly falſely, impudence of falſe Teachers is ſeldome leſſe then blaſphemous, what blaſphemy grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then to give out to be guided by the Spirit of truth, when it is the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of errour all this while; <hi>Thus Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus had his Helena, Mahomet</hi> his dove inured to fetch food out of his ear, is pretended by him to be the holy Ghoſt, whiſpering into his ears, what he ſhould enact for the people.</p>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:52979:63"/>
               <p n="6">6. The ſixt thing meant by ſheeps cloathing is mentioned by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2, 2. word and letter. Theſe falſe teachers pretended they had heard it from Pauls own mouth, and withall forged letters and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered them upon the Apoſtle: for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery is noe new thing in falſe teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and other impoſtures: Apoſtles yet ſurviving, they publiſhed under their names Evangellicall ſtories. Is not the cauſe deplored, which but by ſuch baſe ſhifts cannot be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported?</p>
               <p>The Second marke by which falſe teachers are known is expreſſed by Chriſt in the 7<hi rend="sup">ht</hi> of <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Mat. ver.</hi> 16.20. <hi>by their fruits you ſhall know them,</hi> that is by their falſe doctrine, ſelfe ſeeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and wickedneſs, <hi>ver.</hi> the 23: they work iniquitie 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1.2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which at laſt ſhew what they are, as ripe fruites doe trees. Every one then muſt with the <hi>Nobler ſort of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea, Acts</hi> 17.11. bring the doctrine of falſe teachers to the touchſtone of
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:52979:63"/>the Scripture, and he will ſoone find whether they bee true or falſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Thus the doctrine of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts concerning the Lords Supper will ſoone be found defective, if you compare the ſame with Chriſts firſt inſtitution <hi>Mat,</hi> 26.26. <hi>Mark.</hi> 14.22. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.19, and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24. Their worſhiping of Saints, and praying to them, will be found contrary to Scripture. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2, 1. So all other points wherein we differ.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In like manner Swenkfeldians and Anabaptiſts leading men from the Scriptues to enthuſiaſmes or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate revelations, will ſoone be found falſe by theſe following rules.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In matter of Propheſie, as is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of future things, not interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Scriptures, the event muſt trie it. <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.22.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly. In matter of Doctrine. To the law, and to the teſtimonie, If they ſpeak not according to this word there is noe light in them <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.20. though with ſignes and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:52979:64"/>they ſhould confirme their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, yet if it lead to other Gods Iſraell muſt not attend <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.1.2, 3. Is it another Goſpel, but diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, not contrary to that already received? though <hi>Iſaiah, or Paul, or Peter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> yea an <hi>Angell from Heaven</hi> ſhould publiſh it, we <hi>muſt hold him accurſed. Gal.</hi> 1.8.9.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Queſt.</note>What ſhall ſimple and plaine peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple doe, who know not the points in queſtion between either ſide?</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſ.</note>1. Let them not be careleſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, but remember the caveat of the Apoſtle <hi>Acts.</hi> 20.28. Take heed therefore unto your ſelves, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes your ſoules danger; It is your fault if you be infected and ſeduced: Falſe doctrine is like a Cancer or Gangreene, it frets all that is ſound and in the end killeth. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.17. falſe doctrine puts men beſide their mind or right wits; madneſs ſeizeth them who give way to unſound do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.2. This needes no further evidence then our preſent
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:52979:64"/>daies, in Anabaptiſts, Quakers, their running out of their cloath, ſheweth the running out of their wits. <hi>Paul</hi> ſticks not to impute madneſſe to the ſeduced <hi>Galatians c.</hi> 3.1. &amp; conceits a kind of witchcraft, &amp; ſtrong inchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to poſſeſſe them. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.8. He ſaith they are without Judgment, &amp; <hi>ver.</hi> 9. <hi>fooles.</hi> That clauſe of the admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition in the fore-quoted 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.2. ſhould diſwade levity and unſettled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in matter of faith and religion, becauſe it breedes anxiety, &amp; trouble of mind, reſtleſneſs they do but trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you that bring in another Goſpel. Thus much by way of caveat.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, common people are not ſo ſimple as many make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. I am ſure they are more to be ſtudied then books, they have skill enough in Law, in buying &amp; ſelling you ſhall find them wary and crafty enough. Let them then give atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the word, this will make them wiſe unto ſalvation; let them learn their Catechiſme, which wee may
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:52979:65"/>not unfitly call the little Bible, and out of the ſame they may diſcover falſehood. Catechiſme is that forme of Sound words, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. A ſhort ſumming of the chief heads of faith and charity, unto which we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre all things of Religion; the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riack</hi> calls it holes or boxes, a ſpeech borrowed from Merchants, who have their divers boxes or holes, wherein they put their ſeverall ſorts of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. The chief heads of Catechiſme are ſuch common places.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Learn well to underſtand the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of your faith, &amp; you will eaſily perceive a falſe doctrine againſt faith.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Learn the ten Commandements and you ſhall know, how to carry your ſelves towards God and your neighbours, and eaſily diſcover ſin in thoughts, word and deeds.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Learn to underſtand the Lords prayer and you will know what to pray for to ſupply your wants, and what to pray againſt.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In like manner the Doctrine of
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:52979:65"/>the Sacraments, to ſeal, not to ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple your faith. Parents do Satan great ſervice, in keeping their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren off from this ſo profitable, ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary an exerciſe; directly contrary to that <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.4. <hi>Bring them up in the nurture and admonition of the Lord;</hi> Parents cannot do more for their Children, then make them the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God. It was an heroick Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther who ſaid of a cowardly Son, <hi>Malo filium habere mortuum, quam bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo mutilem,</hi> ſhe wiſhed her Son dead, becauſe unfit for war to fight for his Countrey. How much more ought Chriſtian parents rather wiſh to have no Sons, then they ſhould not be Gods ſervants. <hi>Aulus Fulvius</hi> when his Son was taken in the Conſpiracy with <hi>Catiline,</hi> ſpake thus unto him, <hi>Ego te non Catilinae, ſed patriae genui.</hi> I begot thee not to ſide with <hi>Catiline,</hi> but to ſerve thy Countrey againſt <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiline.</hi> Much more ought we to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour that our Children may fight under Chriſt the Captain of their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:52979:66"/>againſt the World, the fleſh, and the Devil, and not againſt their God: <hi>Zeuxis</hi> having painted a boy carrying grapes, in a basket, obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the birds to peck at them, was angry with himſelf for not painting the boy more lively, which was his chief intent; then ſure the birds durſt never have been ſo bold; If parents had but ſo much care to forme their Children with grace, as they are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſet out their bodies with need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs curioſities, truely thoſe birds of prey, the world, the fleſh, and Devil, would never dare ſo boldly to pecke at their ſoules.</p>
               <p>Fathers and mothers, will you have your Children to be ſervants to be ſervants of God, and heires of heaven, take this courſe</p>
               <p n="1">1. Be ſetled your ſelves in religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, be not carried about with divers and ſtrange doctrines; for it is a good thing that the heart be eſtabliſhed with grace.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly. Then acquaint your Children
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:52979:66"/>with the grounds of truth neceſſarie to ſalvation, by catechiſing: Inure them to read the Scriptures, and to marke ſuch places as confirme Reli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gion, or check corruption of life. Joyne iſſue in this, that as your Children wax in ſtrength and ſtature, ſo they may grow in grace and favour both with God and man. Then you parents may ſtile your ſelves <hi>Naomies,</hi> beautifull,<note place="margin">Ruth.</note> if you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme this; If you neglect it, you will be <hi>Marah,</hi> full of bitterneſs; And your Children <hi>Ichabods,</hi> for the glory of God is departed from them. and ſo they are <hi>Lo-Ammi,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſ.</note> not Gods people.</p>
               <p n="3">3ly, Let common people who have not their ſenſes exerciſed <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.14. namely in the Scriptures, as appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by the oppoſition. They that uſe milke, are inexpert in the word of Righteouſnes, that they may be able to diſcerne betweene doctrine and doctrine, betweene the puritie of the Goſpel, and the impuritie of
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:52979:67"/>Popery, and all errors and hereſies whatſoever: ſuch then I ſay, that are not exerciſed in Scriptures, &amp; points queſtioned are in a ſpecieall manner to beware of falſe teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, as Chriſt bids them, carefully to marke, and avoid falſe teachers and Brethren, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17. The Apoſtle putteth this admonition in the very end of the Epiſtle, to note that amongſt all other things former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly written of, this in eſpeciall is not to be forgotten. We may not keep company with ſuch, leſt we be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted and perverted by them, for our nature is prone to error, and ſlow to truth; It is ſpoken to all; Let them alone, they are blind leaders of the blind <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.14. <hi>Beware of the leaven of the Phariſees</hi> c. 16.6. All are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded to try the ſpirits 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.1. To trie all and keep that which is Good 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.20. Neither to be carried about with divers and <hi>ſtrange doctrines Heb.</hi> 13.9. <hi>nor to be toſſed too and froo, and caried about with
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:52979:67"/>every winde of doctrine.</hi> Such are the Chaffe <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.4. light, exceeding un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant, vaine, uncertaine, mutable, and changeable, they have noe cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſtay. Therefore the winde of Gods wrath will ſuddenly ſcatter, and drive them away. The Apoſtle 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 10. directs his bleſſed Lady.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Not to participate with ſuch indeed that bring not the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of Chriſt; Receive him not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your houſe; why? this ſeemes incivility, may we not receive ſuch till they diſcover what they are, and then turne them out?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Turpius ejicitur quam non admittitur hoſpes.</hi> You ſhall have more a doe to eject ſuch, then to keepe them out at firſt: therefore ſhut up the doores of your houſe againſt them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Not to participate with ſuch in word <hi>ver.</hi> 11. <hi>neither bid him God ſpeed,</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, be ſofarre in ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him any kindneſs in deede, as vouchſafe him not a kind word or greeting, wiſh him no joy, no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:52979:68"/>afford him not a good word, or familiar ſpeech, ſhew no token of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliaritie to him. He renders a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; for he that biddeth him God ſpeed, is partaker of his evil deeds, and if we be partakers of their ſins, we ſhal be partakers of their plagues. Salutation is a ſign of love; we may not love them, therefore not ſo much as ſalute them. <hi>Marcion</hi> the heretick meeting <hi>Iohn the Euangeliſt,</hi> and asking if he knew him; I know thee, replyed the other, <hi>to be the firſt born of the Devil.</hi> Wee muſt not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute ſuch familiarily as we do the ſaints of God, and Brethren in Chriſt, but rather ſhew a deteſtation of them and their Doctrine. As they be our enemies, we ought to love them, and may ſalute them; as they be Gods enemies we muſt hate them: <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 129.21. Shews the manner; do not I hate them, O Lord, that hate thee? yes, I hate them with a perfect hatred: Wee muſt love the nature which God made, hate the evil
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:52979:68"/>which the Devil made. Our houſes ſhould be open to the Preachers and Profeſſors of the Goſpel, but not ſo to corrupt teachers. Reaſons given are theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is a thing diſpleaſing to God, to give entertainement to his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: <hi>Iehu</hi> the ſeer reproved King <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoſaphat</hi> for joyning with Ahab: wouldſt thou help the wicked, and love them that hate the Lord? 1 <hi>Chro.</hi> 19.2. God gave us our houſes, they muſt be for his friends, and not for his Enemies.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Godly will grieve at it, and ſhall we grieve them for whom Chriſt died? <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.15.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It may bring a bad report up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our ſelves, that we like of them and approove them, whereas <hi>wee ought to abſtain from all appearance of evil,</hi> 1 Theſ. 5.22. <hi>And provide things honeſt before God and men,</hi> 2 Cor. 8.21.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It may endanger our own ſouls, their word fretteth as a canker, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:52979:69"/>2.17. It may overrun us and infect us, ere we bee aware.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It may encourage them in their wickedneſſe, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 13.22.</p>
               <p n="6">6. It may pull Gods wrath on our houſes, and us; God bleſſed Poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phar and his houſe for Ioſephs ſake, <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.5. &amp;c. <hi>&amp;</hi> 30.27. <hi>Laban</hi> for <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs</hi> ſake: So the <hi>Shunamitiſh</hi> woman for <hi>Eliſha's</hi> ſake, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 4.17. His curſe will light on thoſe houſes where the adverſaries of his Goſpel are har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured, Therefore when John the Euangeliſt heard that Cerinthus the Heretick was in the houſe with him; let us fly (ſaith he) leſt the bath fall on our heads, this was the practiſe of Gods ſaints at all times.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> May we not at all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with vvicked men, and the Enemies of Religion? Indeed the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. Seems to affirm the like, I have written to you not to keep Company, if any man that is called a Brother be a fornicatour, or covetous, or an ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>later
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:52979:69"/>with ſuch a one no not to eat: Did not our ſaviour eat with pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans and ſinners?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. The Apoſtles meaning is, that we ought not to have any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate familiarity or common u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, and converſation with ſuch: other vviſe in ſome caſe vve are not forbidden ſimply to eat with ſuch. Sith neither the bond of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony is broken by excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, nor ſuch duties hindred, much leſſe cut off thereby, as vve owe one to another, children to their parents, ſubjects to their Prince, ſervants to their Maſters, and neighbour to neighbour, to win one another to God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Concerning Chriſts conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with ſinners and Publicanes, this the Phariſees catch up, to ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniate him to his diſciples, and ſo to alienate their affection, which many now adayes make uſe of to excuſe their diſſolutneſſe; but let Chriſts anſwere ſerve both them
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:52979:70"/>and us. They who be whole need no Phyſitian, as if hee ſaid, I muſt converſe with theſe becauſe they are ſpiritually ſick, and I am the ſouls ſole Phyſician. They are ſinners I am their ſaviour: Chriſt then converſeth with ſinners not to approve their ſinnes, but to bring them off by his exhortations, taking all occaſions to do good, ſo we ſhould take great care to better man. His nature was ſo pure that he could not be infected. Take a Chriſtall glaſſe, pure and clean, fill it with clear water, ſhake it never ſo much it will continue clear, but a little mudd in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome fouleth all, eſpecially being ſtirred: ſo it is with us, the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall dreggs of ſin, are in our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and will ſoon marr all, we muſt therefore take great care how we converſe with others.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Let the great danger of falſe Doctrine perſwade men to beware of falſe teachers, like a
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:52979:70"/>canker it ſoon ſpreads, and if not look'd into killeth eternalie, breaks the bond of nature, cuts all ſinews of humane ſociety, puts va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riance and implacable diſcords in families, ſoweth ſeeds of ſedition in the ſtate, and ruineth all.</p>
               <p>You will ſay God forbid! I ſhall be brought to this. I anſwere; this is but your conceit.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, when Religion is once gone, humanity will not long ſtay after, what can be look't for from inconſtant perſons: thoſe who caſt off Religion, and ſo their God, will ſoon forget, and ſo caſt off their neereſt and deereſt friends. Beſides, this Irreligion is the next way to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly. <hi>Hazael</hi> conceived ſo well of himſelf 2. <hi>Kings</hi> 8.13. <hi>Eliſha</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told all the evill he ſhould doe to the people of Iſrael <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. <hi>burne their ſtrong holds, and ſlay their youth with the ſword, daſhing their Children, ripping their women with child.</hi> Haza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:52979:71"/>ſaid, <hi>but what is thy ſervant a dog?</hi> namely, as a dog, fierce, cruell, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſs? that he ſhould doe this great thing; ſuch barbarous and inhumane cruelties, as no reaſonable man would doe, but ſavage, ravenous, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable beaſts. <hi>Hazael</hi> at this time did not thinke he ſhould doe ſuch cruell acts. <hi>The heart is deceitfull a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things, and deſperately wicked, who can know it? Ier.</hi> 17.9. The fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing hiſtory will confirme it. The occaſion whereof I ſhall ſhew.</p>
               <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Jude</hi> 8.</note> There is a generation of whom two Apoſtles <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeake, that deſpiſeth all Government, and ſpeaketh evill of dignities, out of an erronious judgement, ſeduced by falſe teachers. <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> utterly miſlike all Government and ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on amongſt Chriſtians: It is not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe that <hi>Iude</hi> calleth ſuch <hi>ver.</hi> 8. <hi>dreamers</hi> for ſo indeed they are, and their dreame is this, that ſin is the cauſe of ſubjection, And although it were ordained and allowed to the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:52979:71"/>Jewes becauſe they were but infants, yet fits it not us Chriſtians that are in the ſtate of perfection: A meere dotage, is it not amongſt thoſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Spirits who are free from ſinne, and ſtill perſiſt in the truth. There are Thrones, Dominations, Powers, Principalities, Angells, and Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angells, <hi>Coll.</hi> 1.16. over who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt is far advanced in the heavenly places, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.20, 21. And if man had continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his integrity, yet government ſhould have been <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xor viro, liberi u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>,</hi> inaſmuch as man naturally is ſociable, and diſciplinable. The mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall law commands to honour Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and mother. The end of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is peace with pietie, &amp; honeſty and on man even then ſhould have ſtood in need of another. Finally there is now as great a neceſſitie of magiſtracie as was amongſt the Jewes; and the new Teſtament would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have commanded ſubjection to magiſtrates, or to pray for them, if it were a ſinne for a Chriſtian to be a
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:52979:72"/>magiſtrate. A Chriſtian therefore</p>
               <p n="1">1. May be a magiſtrate.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Is only fit to be a magiſtrate, becauſe no man better knowes the dutie of a magiſtrate.</p>
               <p n="3">3ly. No man can ſo compleatly and perfectly performe the office of a magiſtrate, but he; becauſe no man underſtands the true religion which he is to maintaine, and by which he is to Governe but he, Haveing thus confirmed this truth in oppoſition to the former error, I proceed to the Hiſtory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> The Hiſtorie.</head>
               <p>IN the year of Chriſt Jeſus 1422 and and thereabout; God was pleaſed to excite, and ſtirre up many learned and godlie men, who as other Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes's, ſhould deliver his people out of the Popiſh, more then Egyptian (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſpirituall) ſervitude. Theſe
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:52979:72"/>teaching the libertie of the Goſpel, obtained by Chriſt only from ſinne, Satan, and conſequently eternal fire, a ſpirituall libertie meerly: Certaine fanaticall and fantaſticall people in Germanie tooke occaſion thereby to ſhake of all ſubjection corporall or bodily, wreſting and perverting the former doctrine of grace, they ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly refuſed to be any more ſubject, neither would they pay any tribute. Armes were taken up firſt in Swevia a country bordering on the upper Palatinate, where they tooke the field with two armiesone of them was with much ſlaughter ſcattered, the other about <hi>Hall</hi> tooke the towne of <hi>Weinſpurge</hi> cauſing the garriſon and Earle of <hi>Helfruſtein</hi> to paſſe through the points of their pikes, thence ſome marched to <hi>Wittenberge,</hi> others into Franconia. The former were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne by <hi>Trucheſer,</hi> and with the loſſe of many thouſands fell into the hands of their owne, who made them pay with their lives for their rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:52979:73"/>The other after they had burned 200 caſtles, and noble and gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens houſes innumerable, invaded the citie of <hi>Wirthpurge,</hi> and beſieged the Caſtle, <hi>Lewes Prince of Palatine</hi> overtook them twice at <hi>Pfederſhrine,</hi> with ſingular clemencie calling off his men from ſlaughtering them. But the Biſhop of <hi>Trevers</hi> did not only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimate his, but alſo went before them in crueltie. Thence this fire crept in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Lorraine,</hi> where <hi>Duke Anthony</hi> quenched it with the ſlaughter of 1500 of them: the parts of the Rhine being quieted, on a ſudden all <hi>Thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringia</hi> and <hi>Haſſia</hi> were in armes, one <hi>Munzer</hi> being the ring-leader who with Enthuſiaſmes and ſtrange reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, he pretended to receive by night, ſtirred up the multitude to take up Armes againſt their Prince and Gentrie: one <hi>Piper</hi> furthering his madnes, affirming, to have receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed promiſe divine in a dream, which aſſured him of the victory. the beginnings were ſuccesfull, and the greatneſſe of the prey made
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:52979:73"/>them Joyfull: When on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the Prince of <hi>Haſſia,</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> and Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke,</hi> made towards them with their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; met them on a Mountain neer <hi>Frankhaufen,</hi> where they had fenced themſelves with waggons, and carts, as they conceived, ſufficiently. The Princes pittying the ſeduced multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude made proclamation of pardon, on condition they ſhould lay down their arms, and every one repair home, delivering up the Authors of this rebellion. <hi>Munzer</hi> was now in danger of life; Wherefore in a long oration, he confirms his vocation, &amp; bitterly, as it were with great zeal, inveighs againſt the Princes. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe obſtinate Rebels were ſet upon, who being terrified with the roaring of the Canons, ſang that vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar hymne <hi>Come holy Ghoſt, eternall God, &amp;c.</hi> and moſt of them earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly waited for helpe from above: Which not appearing any where, but to the contrary death on all ſides;
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:52979:74"/>then fled. Thouſands were ſlain in the purſuit, 300 were taken with their Prophet <hi>Munſer.</hi> Who being exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined and charged with the bloud of ſo many thouſand; laught, ſaying; they would have it ſo. At his execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he acknowledged his fault; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted the Princes to clemency, and the reading of the Scriptures, Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the books of Kings, the reſt of the Priſoners received alſo their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. Ten years after 1535. the ſame fire was Kindled again at <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in Weſtphalia, by Bernhard Rotho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Preacher of the Goſpel there, who being ſeduced by <hi>Iohn of Ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> a Tayler, (whom at firſt he had oppoſed ſtrongly) began to Preach and to preſſe Anabaptiſme, a fained ſanctity, publike repentance, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the tale of Rebaptization, begat reſpect and authority to both; whoſe Complices and followers of the City &amp; Countrey about, allured with the rich prey, took the Town houſe, where the <hi>Senators</hi> met about
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:52979:74"/>matters of their State: Depoſe the Biſhop Lord of that City and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try about it, turn out the Senate, and ſo were Authors of a Civill warre, putting to death all who refuſed to be Baptized by them. <hi>Cnipperdolling</hi> acted the Prince, burn'd and pull'd down Churches; to him came Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phicall or divinely inſpired <hi>Iohn Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi> who commanded all gold and ſilver, and bookes, eſpecially the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be brought forth under pain of death, which two young She-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets diſcovered. The money was put into the treaſury, but all the books were burnt publikely; at which when a Smith laught, he was forthwith cruelly put to death by the Prophet, who not long after was himſelf ſlain, making a Sally upon the Biſhops forces beſieging the City. Him ſucceeded <hi>Iohn of Leyden</hi> who removed <hi>Cnipperdolling</hi> from his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Magiſtracy, appointing him to be executioner or hangman; after this being awaked out of a three
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:52979:75"/>dayes ſleep, he appointed twelve Judges by revelation; and polygamy to have as many wives as they plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Theſe twelve govern'd ſo long, till he had gotten into his hands by his Revelations all Kingly power, promiſing no leſſe to himſelf then the Monarchy of the World. Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated he was, and ſolemnely inaugu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, receiving the imperiall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, Crown, Scepter, Sword, and Robe. He ſate in Judgement under a Tent at certain dayes, having his Executioner <hi>Cnipperdolling</hi> ſtill at his elbow, by inſtinct. All this while the Enemies without were not idle; wherefore he prepared his forces to ſally out, inviting them to a Feaſt, and celebrating the Sacrament of the Supper of the Lord, himſelf giving the brad, and his Executioner gave the Cup; but remembring one in Priſon in the midſt of this action, hee goeth out and beheads him with his own hand. Being returned he ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes eight and twenty Apoſtles to
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:52979:75"/>Preach the Goſpel through the World. Who comming abroad were apprehended and executed as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells for ſowing diſcord. After a long ſiege, famine dayly increaſing; one of his Queanes diſcovering her Huſbands deceit, loſt her head. After he Propheſied concerning the Cities deliverance, but in vain; the City be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed by two was taken, <hi>Rothoman</hi> periſhed in the tumult; <hi>King Iohn &amp; Cnipperdolling</hi> were apprehended, and torn in pieces with fiery tongs, their carcaſes were put into Iron Cages, and ſo hanged from the Top of an high Tower, for a warning to us, and ſucceeding Ages.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:52979:76"/>
               <head>The Prayer.</head>
               <p>BLeſſed Lord God, who haſt made all for the glory and honour of thy moſt holy name, and the good of thy Church which is thy ſpouſe, and dear one, under her feet thou haſt put all, in an eſpeciall manner: but that which ſurpaſſeth all is the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to her the oracles of thy word, a favour not afforded to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, no not to any Nation in that clearneſſe as unto us. By this wee cannot but take notice of thy love to us, in bringing us into thy Church, and adding us to them that ſhall bee ſaved, Lord ſuffer us not to flatter our ſelves by reaſon of the outward luſter of thy favours into ſecurity: cauſe us to remember thy proceſſe with <hi>Shilo, Ieruſalem,</hi> and thoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Churches of <hi>Aſia.</hi> Teach us thankfullneſſe whom thou haſt reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for theſe times of ſo clear reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation; Oh give us grace to conſider
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:52979:76"/>the rocke out of which we were hewen, our forefathers the Gentiles, from whoſe loynes we all deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: O let it be a ſhame to us in the dayes of ſo clear light and revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to be found in the wayes of darkneſſe, as Gentiles in the vanity of our mind, having our cogitations darkned. Give us grace to make this our chiefeſt care to pleaſe thee with a double diligence in the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of our calling Generall and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, and ſo redeem our former time miſpent. Grant wee may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge thy ſpeciall favours, thou haſt afforded unto us, before others, in bringing us into thy Church, and unity of faith. O leave us not to le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity or inſtability of Judgement in matters of faith, let us not be hurried about, weathercock-like with every blaſt of vain doctrine; eſtabliſh our hearts that we may hold faſt the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of faith, without any ſo much as wavering, and grow in grace, and while means continue in the
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:52979:77"/>knowledge of our Lord and ſaviour Jeſus Chriſt. Good Lord, open the eyes of thoſe that are ſeduced, that they may ſee, give them hearts to bewail and forſake ſchiſme, hereſy, and infidelity, that ſo they may come out of the ſnare of the divell, and fly from the wrath to come. Bleſſe our Governours ſupreame and ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate; Be thou a Protector to him, and us all: Grant they may uſe their power for the incouragement of thoſe that do well, and the terrour of evill doers, that we under them may lead a peaceable and quiet life, in all Godlineſſe &amp; honeſty. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that all who labour for the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement of Chriſt's Church meet with oppoſition; Satan and his Inſtruments are tormented by them: Lord be thou pleaſed to enable and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en them, make them men of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Spirit. Give them humble Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, that thou mayeſt delight in them; and they that are now met in that Counſel of the Nations, may not
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:52979:77"/>ſeek their own glory, but be content to ſtoop for any ſervice of thy Church and people, and think no office too mean. Give them loving hearts, full of invention, how to glorify our God, &amp; further the good of his ſervants in ſpight of fleſh and bloud; that they may evidence to all the World by the fruitfullneſſe in their places, that they are good Chriſtians, living for others, and not onely for themſelves. Let thy <hi>Thum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mim</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim</hi> be upon thy holy ones; Open, O Lord, a door of Ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance to every faithfull Miniſter, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him inward faculty and fitneſſe, all thoſe gifts which may fit him for thy Miniſtry, give him a mouth, and wiſdome which all his adverſaries, which are encreaſed ſhall not be able to gainſay, or withſtand: none is fit of himſelf, all ſufficiency is of thee, who doſt make able Miniſters. Open a door to thy word to paſſe, remove all lets and obſtacles of Satan, the World, and the fleſh; Give thy Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:52979:78"/>a free courſe, Open the heart of every hearer, that thy word may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; give him the Spirit of wiſdome and revelation in the knowledge of the ſame; enlighten the eyes of their underſtanding, that they may know the hope of their calling, and the riches of that glorious inheritance of the Saints. Perfect the good work thou haſt begun in us, to the day of the Lord Jeſus, and confirme us blamleſs to the end. <hi>So be it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:52979:78" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
